<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the lavvfulnesse of baptizing infants. As also of the present baptisme, as it hath continued in the severall ages of the world, from John Baptist the first beginner thereof. In way of answer to something written by Iohn Spilsberie against the same.</title>
            <author>Barbon, Praisegod, 1596?-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E270_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212355</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870981</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870981</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123379</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78132)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123379)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 45:E270[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the lavvfulnesse of baptizing infants. As also of the present baptisme, as it hath continued in the severall ages of the world, from John Baptist the first beginner thereof. In way of answer to something written by Iohn Spilsberie against the same.</title>
                  <author>Barbon, Praisegod, 1596?-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Bell for Benjamin Allen, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes head Alley at the signe of the Crowne.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: P.B. [i.e. Praisegod Barbon].</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 22nd 1644"; the 5 in imprint date is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123379:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123379:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE LAVVFVLNESSE OF Baptizing Infants. As alſo of the preſent Baptiſme, as it hath continued in the ſeverall ages of the world, from <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> the firſt beginner thereof: In way of Anſwer to ſomething written by IOHN SPILSBERIE againſt the ſame.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Theſ. 5. 12.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Try all things, hold faſt that which is good.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 105. 8.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>He hath remembred his Covenant for ever, the word which he commanded to a thouſand generations.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. 30. 6.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Lord thy God will circumcize thy heart, and the heart of thy ſeed, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>M. Bell</hi> for <hi>Benjamin Allen,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Popes head Alley at the ſigne of the Crowne. 1645.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:123379:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:123379:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Scriptures do inform us of two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall perſecutions rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Satan againſt that innocent part of the Church (to wit, Infants) beſide the perſecutions which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively they at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the reſt of the Church. The firſt was by <hi>Pharaoh, that ſore oppreſſour of Iſrael,</hi> that held them in ſuch <hi>cruell bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</hi> The ſecond was by bloody <hi>Herod.</hi> Our Lord himſelfe in this latter was perſonally concerned, he then being an Infant, and <hi>Rachels Infants</hi> ſuffering for him. In both which it is conſiderable the time when: In the firſt, it was when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were neere deliverance from <hi>Egypts bondage.</hi> The ſecond was when the Deliverer was come to <hi>Sion,</hi> and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance
<pb facs="tcp:123379:3"/> it was neere at hand. In like kinde now in this laſt age; now God is delivering of his Church from the long and ſore bondage of ſpirituall <hi>Babylon</hi> (called <hi>Sodom and Egypt)</hi> he returning to her as in the dayes of old. There is even now alſo a ſore perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt this innocent part of the Church, which is ſo much the more ſad and grievous in theſe three reſpects: Firſt, in that it is raiſed and carried on by ſuch as pretend to be friends and lovers of <hi>Sion</hi> the Church of God; if it were by open and profeſſed enemies, it were more eaſie to be borne. Secondly, in that they pretend to the glory of God this their perſecuting and caſting out a part of his <hi>heritage;</hi> as did of old thoſe that caſt out their brethren, and ſaid, <hi>Let the Lord be glorified, Eſay</hi> 66. by which meanes many are deceived. Thirdly, in that their oppoſition is againſt them in a ſpirituall regard, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt their relation to God, to his Church, to his gracious Covenant, or Covenant of grace: from all which they ſeclude them, driving them out of <hi>Gods heritage,</hi> that they may goe ſerve other gods, ſpoiling them of all their externall rights and priviledges, and ſo leaving them among the dead; to wit, in treſpaſſes and ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> endeavoured to deſtroy, and <hi>Herod</hi> killed a part of this part of the Church. But theſe in a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſenſe have deſtroyed all this part of the Church; not one left alive, in way of relation to God, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed externally in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But this hard and injurious dealing <hi>Jehovah that is mighty, and Jeſus Chriſt that is gracious,</hi> who manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb facs="tcp:123379:3"/> much tender reſpect unto theſe, will plead their cauſe and right their wrong againſt ſuch as riſe up againſt them as he did of old, for he taketh it as done againſt himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Courteous Reader, in the behalfe of theſe innocent Saints, to whom the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is moſt free, they having nothing to bring unto him (no not ſo much as good words) I doe make defence in their cauſe, as touching their right in the Covenant of grace, and part in the Church of God, to whom they having relation as to a father, and are therein bleſſed, as ſuch are <hi>whoſe God is the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I have thought good to offer it to thy view, in regard that a great part of what I have ſaid for them, and againſt their oppoſers, runneth in another line ſomething different from what is uſually pleaded in their behalfe; that it might be conſidered of, together with an anſwer to ſome things controvertable in that way, about the raiſing of Baptiſme pretended to be loſt, but indeed continued by the power of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the defilements of Antichriſt. The exceptions againſt the ſaid continuance I have made anſwer unto, as alſo ſome other particulars handled; all which I have referred to thy judgement, forbearing ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident expreſſions of proofe and full proofe (as is to be found not in a few of this way and others alſo) that in the judgement of the Reader have made proofe of nothing at all. Indeed ſuch confident praiſing of a mans own work is a certaine ſigne of the weakneſſe of it. Uſe thy rightfull liberty (good Reader) in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of what is ſaid, and be impartiall, ſeeing thou art free.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:123379:4"/>
            <p>Now for my particular Opponent, I profeſſe as much reſpect and tender of love to him as to any of that way, and therefore deſire that nothing may be miſconſtrued in regard of the manner of any proceed, nor of any phraſes; wherein I intend no hurt, but to quicken the Reader, and to make the matter more plauſible to ſome that are dull. If any aſke, why I anſwer only a part, and not the whole book publiſhed by my oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite: I anſwer, firſt, that a great part of it was an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſome others, to whom I leave it to make reply if they pleaſe. Secondly, in regard that ſome other part of the Booke is in way of oppoſall of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that hold not alike the truth of the Church and Baptiſme in the defection, but hold the truth of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme only. I might doe them wrong, for want of abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to manage and make out the matter, therefore I have forborn and left it to themſelves, if they pleaſe to make defence.</p>
            <p>In regard ſome part of this Conteſt is of perſonall Reformation and proceed from corrupt wayes; to ſerve God purely, the maine worke of this preſent age, I ſhall take the boldneſſe to forewarne in love and ſobriety all perſons to take heed to their ſetting out at the firſt; for want whereof this and other errours have been fallen into by not a few. A perſon miſſing his way at the firſt ſetting out, the further he goeth the further out and to ſeeke; even ſo it is in this, one errour begetteth another, and another; and there is no end till men ſit down in darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>That perſon that caſt away the truth of his relation to God, to Chriſt, externally, becauſe of defilements, will never be able to make out his relation in a way of
<pb facs="tcp:123379:4"/> purity. Other foundation can none lay then that which is laid already, no not ingard of outward Religion and the ſervice of God. It is ſafeſt keeping to this, leſt men make their eaſe like thoſe that comming from capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ſought their diſcent and could not finde it, and ſo might not be admitted to ſpeciall Ordinances, but by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim, &amp;c. Eſra</hi> 2. 62. 63. Their labour is to be pitied that know not the way to the City; how ſhall ſuch be ever ſtayed in their courſe, or ſetled in their way, or free from errour and changes from one to another, that hold not the truth of Gods holy Ordinances to have continued in the world, but to be ceaſed by meanes of the defilements that have attended them. Conſider of it, courteous Reader, and of the whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing matter, which I commend to thy conſideration and the bleſſing of God, to cauſe thee to profit, which if in any thing thou ſhalt doe I have my deſire, and ſo reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the ſervice of love</hi> P. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:123379:5"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. COntaining an Anſwer to nine Reaſons againſt the baptizing of Infants. fol. 1</item>
               <item>CHAP. II. Containing a diſcovery of the vaine pretence of finding Baptiſme loſt, and fallen out of the world, in the holy Scriptures of God. fol. 17</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. Containing a defence of the judgement of ſuch as hold that Baptiſme hath continued the Ordinance of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the defilements of Antichriſt. fol. 32</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. Containing a defence of their judgement, that hold no right, or orderly miniſteriall Church, without or before Baptiſme. fol. 57</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123379:5"/>
            <head>A Defence of the lawfulneſſe of the Baptizing Infants.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Containing an Anſwer to reaſons ſet downe in page</hi> 25. <hi>why Infants ſhould not be Baptized; the ſeverall Reaſons being ſet downe in order, their ſeverall and reſpective An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers doe follow.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>I</label> 
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe there is neither command nor example for the baptizing Infants in the New Teſtament; the order and government of which is no way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to the old: But in the old there was an expreſſe rule by command from God what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants were to be admitted to Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and other Ordinances of that nature, and what not: But this order is no where found in the New Teſtament for the baptizing of Infants, and therefore the ſame is not to be practiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> This firſt Reaſon placed in the front is wholly upon ſuppoſition, concluding, and ſo taking that for granted which is wholly in controverſie, and the contrary as confidently affirmed by his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents as denyed by him (namely, <hi>That there is neither Precept nor Example for baptizing Infants)</hi> which they affirme there is. Againe, this Reaſon is wholly by way of deduction and inference, without any Scripture either for ground or confirmation of it, of which he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123379:6"/> complaineth in his Epiſtle, and yet he practiſeth it himſelfe, and that in his firſt Reaſon.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is obſervable how he by this Reaſon excludeth a great and maine part of the Scripture, namely, <hi>neceſſary conſequence,</hi> and <hi>right inference,</hi> being ſuch a way as our Lord himſelfe uſed to confute the Sadduces withall,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 22. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the God, &amp;c.</hi> God is not the God of the dead: here is neither command nor example, and yet the truth fully evinced, the minde of God manifeſted, and the Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces confuted.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is an unſound concluſion, that becauſe there is no command or example in the New Teſtament, therefore not to be done. There is no particular example nor particular command for womens partaking in the Supper, yet they are judged lawfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants. There is no example nor particular command for tranſlation of Scriptures, or that ſuch tranſlations be uſed in Church-meetings, yet it is lawfully done. Laſtly, there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or example for an unbaptized perſon to baptize himſelfe or others. So as if this firſt Argument were true, <hi>I. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way would be in a poore caſe.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it is untrue that which he inferreth, there being both example and precept in the Scripture for the baptizing of Infants, though he cannot ſee it, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. compared with <hi>Eſay</hi> 52. 15. which ſhall be further ſhewed hereafter in making it to appeare that children are yet a part of the Church; and ſo, both precept and example being for the waſhing of the whole, it muſt include them neceſſarily as a part, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 26.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>II</label> 
                  <hi>It is a high contempt and injury to Chriſt, as he is Husband of the Church his holy Spouſe, to force on him a naturall wife, himſelfe being ſpirituall, and deſires the like aſſociate; as ſuch a Church is founded upon nature, namely, Infants; becauſe commonly to one borne of the Spirit there is twenty borne of the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, here is a high charge without proofe, no Scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for confirmation. Is not this rather a high contempt and preſumption? Is it not a ſad thing that a man ſhould fall under the condemnation of his owne law, or otherwiſe exempt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from that which he will binde others unto (namely, to bring the Scriptures and not conſequences?</p>
               <p>Secondly, this Reaſon accuſeth God himſelfe, in giving the Church of old, namely, thoſe ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> by generation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123379:6"/> (which he calleth carnall) to Chriſt his Sonne to wife; Jeſus Chriſt our Lord being the ſame ſpirituall Head and Husband, <hi>Ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, and to day, and for ever, Heb.</hi> 13. 8.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is no injury to Chriſt or contempt of him (though without any Word of God he ſo ſay) for Chriſt <hi>to have the heathen</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>given him for inheritance, and the ends of the earth for his poſſeſſion.</hi> It is no injury to him (though the Diſciples thought it was) to have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children brought to him, his Kingdome conſiſting of ſuch (in quantity as well as quality) <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 13.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, why cannot Children be ſpirituall and holy as well now under the Goſpell as they were under <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moſes;</hi> when they as well as thoſe of yeers were <hi>an holy people to the Lord God</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 19. 6, 7 Dent. 6, 7. Eſay 9. 2.</note>? and the ſame is ſaid of the Church now: <hi>but ye are an holy Nation, a peculiar people,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. Beſide, what ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was there in the five fooliſh <hi>Virgins</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 25,</note>, I would know, that is not, or may not be in children? and is not there as much injury offered to Chriſt in giving them to Chriſt to wife? Truly this is weake and inconſiderate ſo to reaſon, not minding that <hi>many are called, and few choſen, Matth.</hi> 22. 14.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this Reaſon is wholly upon ſuppoſition, the accuſation without proofe: who forceth on Chriſt? It is his pleaſure to take ſuch, and reproveth ſuch as would hinder them, and ſaith, <hi>Suffer ſuch to come, they being of my Kingdom, Matth.</hi> 22. The computation in the end is as weake as all the reſt, for it was ſo of old, no new thing at all; <hi>all are not Iſrael that are of Iſrael,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 9. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>and if the number of Iſrael were as the ſand of the ſea, but a remnant ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>III</label> 
                  <hi>It is a practiſe that over throwes the body of Chriſt or holy temple of God, for in time it will come to conſiſt of naturall and carnall members; amongſt whom if any godly be, they will be brought into bondage, and become ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of ſcorne and contempt, and the power of government reſt in the hands of the wicked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> This is but onely ſaid, and that by one that may erre and be miſtaken. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> though ſent of God, yet he <hi>cryeth, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 3. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>I. S.</hi> is a ſtranger in his reaſons to what is written, though, as we noted before, he doth account it ſuch a faulty thing in others, yet he pleaſeth himſelfe all along in his reaſons to infer this and the other thing to little purpoſe, unleſſe to deceive.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this practice of old (namely of propagating the Church by generation) was ſo far from deſtroying the Church, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123379:7"/> that it did tend to the increaſe of it greatly, and was a meanes of <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 20. 22. 17. 26 4 24. Eſay 4. 8, 19. Pſal. 105. 8.</note> the continuing of it according to the gracious Covenant of God to a thouſand generations, and his promiſe to the ſeeds ſeed. <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 59. 14.</note> Now that Covenant is yet in force, and that promiſe <hi>Yea, and Amen</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> as are all other of like nature.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this is an inference ſavouring of ignorance, or elſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, or both; hath not God ſaid <hi>that he will poure his Spirit upon their ſeed</hi> (to wit of his Church) <hi>and his bleſſing upon</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Eſay 44. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>their off-ſpring? and that all their children ſhall be</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 54. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>taught of God?</hi> that his Church ſhall be <hi>a praiſe in the world</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Eſay 62. 7.</note> when he ſhall returne in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to <hi>Sion,</hi> that <hi>the Gentiles ſhall bring their riches to her</hi> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 60.</note>? nay, hath he not ſaid, <hi>that the kingdome and greatneſſe thereof ſhall be given to the Saints of the moſt high,</hi> 
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Dan. 7. 27.</note> and that <hi>this honour have all the Saints</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal 144 9.</note>?</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, what ever is or can be conceived in this reaſon, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the parts of it or the whole put together, cannot amount to make good the charge, the whole ſuppoſed proofe reaching but to the wel-being and purity of the Church at the moſt, and not to the being of it, it being ſo far from deſtroying of it, as is affirmed; the which I leave to the judgement of the Reader.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>IV</label> 
                  <hi>It is unlawfull to baptize Infants, becauſe it is a ground both of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and errour; for it holds people in blindneſſe, that they cannot come to ſee and know the nature of that holy Ordinance, nor what the ſame requires in the ſubjects thereof; and alſo it cauſeth the ſimple to conceive that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is of neceſſity to ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> That it is ſo as this Reaſon affirmeth, if any pleaſe to beleeve it they may; ſure there is no Word of God produced to enforce them, nor yet good reaſon or neceſſary conſequence, which the Author diſliketh in others, to move them to it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this Reaſon ſavoureth of arrogancy, and intrencheth on the wiſdome of God that eſtabliſhed this very thing in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it in circumciſion of old, it being then no ground of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance nor errour; neither is it now, though he ſo ſay, there being no more cauſe given to ſimple now to thinke ſo of Baptiſme, then was given them then in caſe of Circumciſion. Indeed it is rather likely their keeping ſuch adoe about Baptiſme, and building ſuch high things thereon may occaſion ſome ſtrange thoughts to ſuch as are ſimple, as ſurely it doth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I aske what ſhould be the reaſon they cannot ſee the nature of the ordinances, &amp;c. The Baptizing of Infants doth not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123379:7"/> let or hinder the knowledge of perſons of yeers, thoſe are not the perſons he meaneth ſurely; for I appeale to himſelfe, whether he in particular be hindred at all thereby. Nay further, it hindreth not Infants when they come to yeers from underſtanding the nature and ends of the Ordinance, no more then it did in the caſe of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion the Iſraelites of old; it being Gods appointment, <hi>that children</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 4.</note> now, as of old, ſhould <hi>bee trained up in knowledge and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> If any be hindred from underſtanding the nature and ends of this Ordinance, ſuch are a great cauſe of it, in regard of many that are of the judgement and practice of <hi>I. S.</hi> who being ſo mutable in their courſe, one while laying downe, another time taking up, and then caſting away againe. And beſide altering the ends of Baptiſme and rejecting the proper ſubjects of it, namely, the lineall ſeed of the faithfull, that many they converſe withall are at their wits end, and know not what to hold or ſettle upon. And that it is ſo, and alſo that this reaſon hath no force in it againſt the baptizing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, I leave the Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>It keepeth up the ſtate of Antichriſt, by granting of him this ſo chiefe a corner-ſtone of the Lords Houſe to lie in his foundation; for that Church where Baptiſme is the true ordinance of God in the adminiſtration of it, is by the rule of the Goſpel a true Church; ſo that if Antichriſts Baptiſme, which he adminiſtreth be Gods Ordinance, then that Church wherein he doth ſo adminiſter the ſame muſt be alſo the Church of God, and thoſe in ſinne that refuſe communion with it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> It may here be minded that divers things are here in this Reaſon affirmed and concluded, but nothing at all proved; we know what is written <hi>to the Law and Teſtimony, Eſay</hi> 8. 20. but <hi>I. S.</hi> ſeemeth to be a ſtranger to that, and chuſeth inferences, ſuch as he found great fault with in his Epiſtle. No man needs to beleeve what is ſaid in this Reaſon unleſſe he will.</p>
               <p>Secondly, who granteth this to lie in the foundation of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? ſurely <hi>I. S.</hi> ſurmiſeth and taketh for granted that which is not acknowledged; if any doe or have done, it is not for want of ignorance. <hi>Jeroboam</hi> made a ſchiſme, ſet up an idolatrous way of worſhip and calves; and yet notwithſtanding that way of his, there was Circumciſion, the Ordinance of God, and no part of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his idolatrous way, nor any corner-ſtone in the building thereof. Neither is Baptiſme now any more a part of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Antichriſt, or corner-ſtone in that building. And if <hi>I. S.</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:123379:8"/> were not ignorant of this myſtery of iniquity, he would not thus reaſon as he doth. <hi>This myſtery of iniquity it wrought</hi> in the Church <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.</note> in the Apoſtles time, when Baptiſme was Gods Ordinance, and no part of that foundation or corner-ſtone in that building, as neither is now any part of it. Let <hi>I. S.</hi> if he can, ſhew when Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme became ſuch a corner-ſtone in the foundation of that build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; or why it ſhould be ſo, more then Circumciſion of old was a corner-ſtone in that idolatrous ſtate and way of <hi>Jeroboam and the Calves:</hi> let him ſhew how long it continued Gods holy Ordinance, and when it ceaſed ſo to be.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Chriſt is the chiefe corner-ſtone,</hi> and this corner-Stone is in <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 20.</note> that deſſection (yet no part of it;) I ſuppoſe <hi>I. S.</hi> granteth it, and will not deny it, That there is in many in this Kingdome (eſpecially) and <note place="margin">John Hus &amp; alia.</note> elſe where, as it was alſo formerly, ſuch as in whom Chriſt and his Word and Spirit dwell, yet are not come out of that ſtate accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his ſenſe. Now to grant this is more likely to keep up the ſtate of Antichriſt; and to deny this ſure he dare not. Let him ſee how he will avoid his own Argument upon his own ground: Surely ſome have ſeene this, and thereupon have held no faith, no grace, no Chriſt till ſo ſeparated from <hi>Babylon.</hi> Sure he muſt either renounce his reaſon or fall under the condemnation of it, if he be true to his owne principle. In this particular that now I ſet downe, if my judgement faile me not, he will never be able to avoid it, by grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures tranſlated to be the Word of God, and uſefull in the Church; which <hi>Babylon</hi> hath tranſlated, keepeth and holdeth forth and buildeth upon. Now for him and others to receive, hold, and keep the ſame, and to acknowledge them as Gods, it muſt ſure be, according to his reaſon, a keeping up the ſtate of Antichriſt, by granting this foundation to his building, and this corner-Stone Jeſus Chriſt; for of the Scriptures its ſaid, <hi>and are built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Chriſt the chiefe corner</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Stone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now in ſtead of the Word of the Lord, for proofe of what he had affirmed in his reaſon, he giveth onely his owne ſaying to very little purpoſe ſurely; That Church, ſaith he, where Baptiſme is the true Ordinance of God (as if God had ſome falſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) in the adminiſtration of it. Obſerve, he hath got the word <hi>true</hi> to helpe him along; that Church, ſaith he, by the rules of the Goſpel is a true Church; what rule or rules he meaneth is hard to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123379:8"/> gueſſe, he ſetteth downe no place of Scripture. Againe, it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable how he cloſeth with them he oppoſeth, making the Word and Sacraments infallible marks of the Church; yea, one of them alone, to wit, <hi>Baptiſme.</hi> And yet he holdeth a Church may be Chriſts without Baptiſme, as in his book may be ſeen.</p>
               <p>He inferreth further, and thereby will prove (for want of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) that if Baptiſme be true, the Church is true. I aske Maſter <hi>I. S.</hi> if the Apoſtate ten tribes were a true Church, for it is certaine their Circumciſion was true. So as here the Reader may ſee how he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Church and Baptiſme ſuch ſpeciall relatives, as the one gives being to the other, as the father doth to the ſonne, &amp;c. and yet he holdeth an unbaptized Church, as we noted before.</p>
               <p>He addeth further, That it being the Church of God, it is ſinne in any not to communicate with her. A confident charge, but where is the proofe? alas, it is altogether wanting: Communion with a Church is the queſtion to which I ſhall ſay a little, and leave the Reader to judge. Firſt, I diſtinguiſh of Churches; ſecondly, of Communion: Churches are either pure and undefiled, or otherwiſe corrupt, and in ſundry things polluted. Communion, it is either gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, conſiſting in owning, acknowledging, and ſtanding for, or it is ſpeciall and peculiar in fellowſhip and worſhip.</p>
               <p>Now for a Church corrupt and defiled, generall communion only can lawfully be extended; eſpecially, if ſhe be greatly defiled, for we may <hi>not partake of others ſins,</hi> though we are to own their vertues and good things that are in them, and hold relation to them while they <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 22.</note> hold the head: but with a pure Church we may and ought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend communion in all the parts of communion. But the queſtion being of communion with a corrupt Church, I ſay, we are to hold generall communion with the ſame, and to owne it for the relation it hath to Chriſt, ſo long as it holdeth the head. And if particular communion in Ordinance can be extended without partaking in ſinne, we ſhould not be wanting that way, as occaſion is offered. But though with ſuch a Church in generall, and further as we can without ſinne, yet not with her in ſinne; we are to <hi>keepe our ſelves pure,</hi> as before. And in this caſe, that is very conſiderable, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. 4. <hi>Come out of her, my people, that ye partake not of her ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that here I both grant and alſo deny that which <hi>I. S.</hi> affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. I grant, if it be a Church, though corrupt, yet ſo long as it hath relation to Chriſt, it is ſinne not to owne her and acknowledge
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123379:9"/> her relation. I wiſh <hi>I. S.</hi> were free from this ſinne that condemneth as no Churches of Chriſt all the Churches of God in the world; onely thoſe of his way. I pray him to conſider of it.</p>
               <p>I alſo deny what he ſaith, being referred to that ſpeciall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in ordinance and worſhip, which we are bound no further un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to then as we may partake with them without ſinne and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the ſeven thouſand could not, might not, ought not to have bowed to <hi>Baal, or kiſſed the calves, or gone to Gilgal to tranſgreſſe;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 4. Hoſea 13. 2. Hoſea 4. 15. Amos 5. 5.</note> nor yet joyne with thoſe Prieſts made of the loweſt of the people, yet were they the Church of God, and Circumciſion and other of Gods Ordinances might be done lawfully of them. Yea, thoſe of the Church did not ſinne in abſtaining communion in <hi>Judah</hi> it ſelfe in the time of <hi>Ahaz</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes;</hi> for, as in going to <hi>Gilgal,</hi> ſo in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> they ſhould have tranſgreſſed.</p>
               <p>All which conſidered, I conceive it will appeare to be very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous which <hi>I. S.</hi> affirmeth of Infants Baptiſme keeping up the ſtate of Antichriſt; for indeed the contrary is rather true, That the deniall of them right to that holy Ordinance, doth rather keepe up that ſtate by the hardning them, that otherwiſe would come out. And alſo by the great confuſion (like another <hi>Babel)</hi> which this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and practice produceth. All which I leave to the judgement of the godly wiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>VI</label> 
                  <hi>It is unlawfull to baptize Infants, for that is to build faith upon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane teſtimony in matters fundamentall; for ſuch as are baptized in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, have no other way to ſatisfie themſelves or others but the bare word of man that muſt ſtand in the place of the Word of God, for ſuch their truly receiving ſo holy an Ordinance of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> This Reaſon is very unlike, <hi>I. S.</hi> he promiſeth faire for gravity and wiſdome, &amp;c. but ſurely ſuch a ſhallow and unſound Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was never framed before: I ſuppoſe it is not his owne, but that he hath received it without conſideration from ſome one that he was highly taken withall; and being a new thing, it pleaſed him, and he ſet it amongſt his reaſons why he would not have chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren baptized, that they might be ſomething for number, though nothing in ſubſtance and weight.</p>
               <p>His ſcope is eaſie, but his expreſſions darke and covert; I ſhall goe over them by way of <hi>quere.</hi> Firſt, I would faine know what faith he here meaneth, whether Hiſtoricall or of ſome other kinde. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I would know what he meaneth by building faith upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123379:9"/> humane teſtimonies. Thirdly, I would know what he meaneth by matters fundamentall, and how the receipt of the Ordinance can be a matter fundamentall, when the perſon may not onely be matter, but part of a Church without it, as he holdeth. Fourthly, I would know how the word of man ſtands in the place of the Word of God, and what he meaneth by the bare word of man in this matter of fact. Laſtly, I would know what he meaneth by truly receiving this holy Ordinance (and whither he hold there be a falſe receiving this Ordinance, and yet the Ordinance holy and true to them that receive it. This Reaſon, as it is ſet down, I take to be ſomething like a ſpell.</p>
               <p>The ſumme of it in other words. I take to be this, Infants are not to be baptized, for that they cannot be aſſured when they come to yeers that they were baptized, but by the witneſſe of man; and if that fail, then there is no way of ſatisfying of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they were at all baptized.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer; firſt, that I would not much ſtrive with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in ſuch a caſe: If that were the cauſe that the probableneſſe of his not being at all Baptized were the cauſe that moved him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be Baptized; eſpecially if it did appeare to them by whom he ſhould ſeek to be Baptized, that he had not been Baptized at all. But ſurely this is far from the caſe in queſtion; wherein men get themſelves baptized: not that they thinke they were not bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at all, but that they judge it was not the Baptiſme of Chriſt, becauſe of the corruptions in the ſubject, inſtrument, or the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their being baptized, which made the matter null and void.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I would have it minded how a perſon circumciſed in youth could be aſſured when he came to yeers, eſpecially if his Circumciſion were gathered and grown, ſo as he could not ſee the print in the fleſh: For this Reaſon, if it hath any force in it, it hath the ſame againſt Circumciſion in Infancy as againſt Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; for ſuch ſo circumciſed, could be no otherwiſe aſſured then ſuch a way as will come within the compaſſe of humane teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. If it be ſaid, They might ſatisfie themſelves by the ſight of the print of the fleſh; I anſwer, that might be gathered and grown ſo as not to be ſeen. And again, if it were not, that fight is not the Word of God; and beſide, they might be miſtaken, or be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed unlawfully.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:123379:10"/>
               <p>Thirdly, that others were circumciſed of old, or are baptized now, eſpecially thoſe to be joyned with in publike Ordinances and ſpeciall communion. Now how could the Iſraelites know of old, or how can it be known now in particular, how will <hi>I. S.</hi> to put the caſe to himſelfe, how will he, I ſay, know and be aſſured that ſuch and ſuch as he holdeth communion withall are baptized, but by humane teſtimony, inſtead of the Word of God, as he ſaith; he muſt take their own word in their own caſe, whether it be not humane, I leave it to him to judge.</p>
               <p>And I demand further, whether upon this his ground any can in faith joyn in fellowſhip and ſpeciall communion, or could of old with any they did not ſee or have not ſeen circumciſed of old, <note place="margin">Epheſ. 44. 9.</note> or Baptized now in this diſpenſation of the Goſpell; for ſuppoſe they were Baptized in <hi>Holland</hi> or in ſome part of this Kingdom, nay in this City, and I not ſee it done, where am I then? by his ground, I muſt beleeve the bare word of man in ſtead of the Word of God in a matter alike fundamentall according to his account.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, in matter of fact, I judge Faith of ſuch a nature as we have now in hand, is to goe upon humane teſtimony (if <hi>I. S.</hi> will have it ſo called) and that ſuch teſtimony is of divine autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and every way ſatisfactory to be reſted in; for <hi>at the mouth of two or three witneſſes every truth ſtands ratified.</hi> In matter of fact, I <note place="margin">Matth. 18. 16.</note> make it appear thus:</p>
               <p>That ſuch a people are Chriſts Church; a Church being a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall thing, mens witneſſes muſt carry it and give ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, eſpecially in regard of the firſt beginning of a Church, which ſome much ſtand upon.</p>
               <p>Again, that ſuch a perſon is the lawfull Miniſter of Chriſt and his Church lawfully choſen and ordained, what way is there of ſatisfaction but the word of man to any but onely to thoſe that were at the acting of it?</p>
               <p>Excommunication is an ordinance alike fundamentall with Baptiſme, it is to be done in faith; the practike part of it is to be built upon the teſtimony of men, <hi>at the mouth of two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes;</hi> ſo as here expreſly the word, the bare word of man carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame.</p>
               <p>So as I conclude, as this reaſon is a fooliſh fancy, ſo it premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth wholly upon untruth, and raiſeth unprofitable doubts, and hath the ſame force againſt other Ordinances of Chriſt as it hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123379:10"/> againſt Baptiſme of Infants, that it can by no means reach ſo high, as to hinder Infants Baptiſme, all which I leave to the judgement of the Reader.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>7</label> 
                  <hi>To baptize Infants, makes the Ordinance of God a lying ſigne, becauſe none of thoſe things can be expected in an Infant, which the ſaid Ordinance holds forth or ſignifieth in the adminiſtration of it; which is the parties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and ſpirituall new birth, a dying and buriall with Chriſt, in reſpect of ſin, and riſing with him in a new life to God, and a confirmation of faith in the death and reſurection of Chriſt, and free remiſſion of ſins by the ſame, as</hi> Rom. 6. 3, 4. <hi>none of all which can be expected in an Infant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> This is a lying accuſation, of a malignant ſpirit, againſt a holy practiſe of an Ordinance of Gods own appointment, for might not any one as truly have ſaid thus of Circumciſion of Infants of old, aſwell as of the Baptiſme of Infants now; for what could be expected of an Infant then, that cannot be now. Did not Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion call for, and lead unto then, as much as Baptiſme doth now? did not Circumciſion call for Circumciſion of heart? <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>being, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the heart, not of the letter, the praiſe whereof is of God, not of men,</hi> did it not alſo call <hi>for regeneration, and newneſſe of life?</hi> were not the Infants of it ſpirituall above the reach of the creature, eſpecially children, yet it was then no lying ſigne, as <hi>I. S.</hi> in the caſe of Baptiſme lyingly affirmeth?</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſay, our Lord was baptized, and this Ordinance was no lying ſigne, as it was acted on him; yet thoſe things were not in him, nor could be, which <hi>I. S.</hi> ſaith, the Ordinance holdeth forth or ſignifieth, <hi>namely, Regeneration, a ſpirituall new life, dying to ſin, burying with Chriſt, riſing with him in newneſſe of life, confirmation of faith, and free remiſſion of ſins by the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What will <hi>J. S.</hi> ſay now, will he ſay it was a living ſigne, or will he confeſſe his lying accuſation, to be, as indeed it is, lying and falſe, for none of thoſe things which he is pleaſed to ſet downe, as held forth in Baptiſme, or elſe it is a lying ſigne, could be expected, much leſſe be, in Chriſt: And yet <hi>he fulfilled righteouſneſſe,</hi> in being <note place="margin">D. <hi>Sclater</hi>
                  </note> baptized, as is righteouſneſſe fulfilled in Infants Baptiſme, even as it was in their Circumciſion of old.</p>
               <p>For we may know, that there are other ends in Baptiſme, as there was in Circumciſion of old, beſides thoſe ſpecified by <hi>J. S.</hi> as namely, the ſubjecting the creature, and dedicating of him to God outwardly in a way of ſervice. The marking of him for God by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123379:11"/> ſuch a Character. The differencing of him from the reſt of the World, and inſtructing in inward ſanctification by the outward waſhing.</p>
               <p>And here it may be obſerved, that at length <hi>J. S.</hi> quoteth a Scripture or two, but to little purpoſe ſurely; it is about dipping, for that is new, and pleaſeth him; and ſo in his ſeventh Reaſon at length he commeth out with it. So he concludeth, <hi>None of all which can be expected in an Infant:</hi> And why not, but only becauſe he ſaith ſo; but his words are no Oracles: for thoſe, or ſome of thoſe may be found in Infants, notwithſtanding what he ſaith. God that works thoſe in an elder, can work them in a Infant, he hath done it as in the caſe of <hi>Jeremy, John Baptiſt,</hi> he hath promiſed to do it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 6. <hi>And all Gods promiſes are yea &amp; Amen in Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 10. Which when <hi>J. S.</hi> hath conſidered of, he may repent of his error and lying accuſation, as indeed he hath great cauſe for to do.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe the indifferent Reader will be able to ſee how falſe and unworthy an accuſation this is, which makes Chriſt himſelf an unlawfull ſubject, and Baptiſme a lying ſigne to him; if <hi>J. S.</hi> his accuſation were true, in as much as thoſe things could not be expected, or be at all in Chriſt, which he ſpecifies as neceſſary, or elſe it is ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>Becauſe the ſubject of Baptiſme is to be paſſive; but a Infant is no way paſſive, as that Ordinance requires, I mean a paſſive ſubject in a threefold way. Firſt, a thing uncapable, and ſo is a ſtone. Secondly, a thing forced, and thus is a Infant that oppoſeth it Baptiſme what it can, ſo far is it from being paſſive in the ſame. Thirdly, a thing is paſſive by a ſubjecting power producing the ſame in the ſubject, by bringing of it into a free and volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubjection, and thus is the true ſubject of Baptiſme, none can be capable to receive grace but by grace, becauſe it conſiſts of ſelf-denyall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, it is marvelous to ſee how contrary and different, theſe men are in their Tenents. <hi>A. R.</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Childiſh Baptiſme,</hi> maketh Children to be uncapable Subjects, becauſe they are meer paſſive, as he is pleaſed to ſay: whereas the right ſubjects of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme (he ſaies) ought to be more then paſſive: <hi>J. S.</hi> he maketh them uncapable, becauſe they are not paſſive at all; as contrary as theſe men are one to another, even ſo contrary is their opinion to the truth. Namely, their denying Baptiſme to Infants: as untrue alſo is that which he further addeth, that an Infant is no way paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, as that Ordinance requires. What that Ordinance requires
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123379:11"/> in a paſſive way, that is not, or cannot be in an Infant in a paſſive way; ſure <hi>J. S.</hi> cannot ſhew. Infants were paſſive in Circumciſion of old, ſo were perſons of years; and there was no reall differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in paſſiveneſſe, or being patients in that Ordinance of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, as there is none now in Baptiſme, betwixt Infants and men of years, though <hi>J. S.</hi> would by a fooliſh diſtinction of the divers kindes of paſſiveneſſe, ſeek to make it appear otherwiſe. He firſt ſpeaketh of a ſtones being paſſive, but this he ſaith <hi>is uncapable;</hi> of what is it uncapable? not of totall dipping, no not in a paſſive way. <hi>J. S.</hi> may pleaſe to remember, what is written of ſuch like ſubjects, namely, <hi>The baptizing of cups and pots, &amp;c.</hi> which ſure he <note place="margin">Mark. 7. 4.</note> forgot, elſe he would not have diſtinguiſhed ſo; <hi>Secondly for an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, which he ſaith oppoſeth its Baptiſme what it can;</hi> I ſay it oppoſeth its Baptiſme no more then it did in Circumciſion of old. But how knoweth he they oppoſe their Baptiſme, becauſe happily they ſhrine and cry; a waighty reaſon ſure: did not Infants, nay, did not perſons of years in Circumciſion do the like: yea more, do not perſons of years ſhrinke and ſhew an unwillingneſſe to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally dipped in <hi>J. S.</hi> his way.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>For paſſiveneſſe by a ſubjecting power, bringing a thing to a free and voluntary ſubjection;</hi> which is, as he ſaith, <hi>the true ſubject:</hi> It may be obſerved how he rubbeth upon the old ſore, there is ſomthing in Infants wanting, ſome Faith, ſome Repentance, ſome Freeneſſe, ſome willingneſſe of ſubmiſſion, which he is pleaſed to make paſſive qualifications, with little reaſon ſurely: for any man may ſee what the diſeaſe is, they bring nothing to Chriſt, therefore they muſt have no acceptance of him, nor grace from him. Indeed it is works and not grace that here lets: For certainly Infants are as capable of grace, and grace as free to them, as to perſons of years. As both old and young are meer paſſive, in regard of inward grace, and God giveth freely; ſo both are alſo alike paſſive, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of outward grace, to wit, that <hi>of the</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Covenant,</hi> and this in queſtion in particular, namely Baptiſme, the Seale of it: even as in Circumciſion of old. But he hath a kinde of reaſon, although no Scripture, to prove either his diſtinction, or that children are not paſſive; and that is, <hi>That none can be capable to receive grace but hy grace, becauſe it conſiſts of ſelf-denyall.</hi> Truly, this had need of ſome explaining, ſurely our being ſinners and miſerable, maketh us meet ſubjects for mercy: I reckon, that there is nothing in us,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123379:12"/> (as of our own) of grace, that can make us capable. I ſuppoſe he holdeth not with the Papiſts foreſeen works or any preparatives that maketh perſons capable of grace. If he mean thus, that none can be capable of the grace of Baptiſme, in an orderly way, but by being within the grace of the Covenant firſt, I ſhould agree with him, and do think, that nothing can be more clear, but that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, being within the Covenant, and intereſſed in the grace of God that way, they are capable of further grace, namely, to be ſealed with the Seale thereof, Baptiſme. But what he meaneth I I know not, becauſe he ſaith <hi>It conſiſts of ſelf-denyall;</hi> If he be able to apply it to the purpoſe now in hand, I ſhall be willing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my want of judgement, for to me it is, as if he had ſpake of a man in the Moon: and how far this eight reaſon is from effecting any thing againſt the lawfulneſſe of Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, I leave it to the Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>9</label> 
                  <hi>This Doctrine of Infants Baptiſme oppoſeth directly the expreſſe Word of God, by teaching that Infants are in the Covenant of Grace; being borne of believing parents, and ſo a holy ſeed, by vertue of which they have right to Baptiſme, as a priviledge of grace. Againſt which the holy Ghoſt affirms, that all are conceived in ſin, and brought forth in iniquity, and ſo by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the children of wrath, and under the curſe, and except they be horne againe, they cannoe ſee the Kingdome of God,</hi> Pſal. 51. 5. <hi>&amp;c. Here man ſaith, that Infants are clear and holy from the wombe, and ſo are ſubjects of grace: But God ſaith, all Infants, as well one as other, are firſt in ſin, and unholy, and ſubjects of wrath, untill the ſecond birth makes the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> John 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> At the length <hi>I. S.</hi> hath attayned to the full number of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which are far more by number then by weight, and ſurely this laſt is not in the leaſt behinde the other for ſhallowneſſe; for either he was very ignorant of what he ſet down, or elſe perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit carryed him headlong to the multiplying of words without councell againſt the truth. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, I would ask of <hi>I. S.</hi> whether <hi>Iſaac and Jacob, and the Infants of Iſrael,</hi> were not in the Covenant of Grace? whether he and they were not a holy ſeed? by vertue of which they had right to Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and priviledge of Grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 29. That the Covenant to <hi>Abraham</hi> was a Covenant of Grace, I ſuppoſe he denyeth not; that Circumciſion was a priviledge of Grace, the Seale of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant the Apoſtle teſtifieth in the caſe of <hi>Abraham, He received it as the Seal of the righteouſneſſe of faith,</hi> Rom. 4. 11.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:123379:12"/>
               <p>Secondly, I would know whether <hi>Iſaac, the particular Son of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>with Jacob fellow-heire,</hi> were not borne in ſin? and whether he or they in Infancy were under wrath; ſo as he could not be in the Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I would ask him, whether children, being out of the Covenant of Grace, and born in ſin, and ſo under wrath. accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his ſenſe, can poſſibly be converted, ſo as <hi>to ſee heaven,</hi> if they <note place="margin">John 3. Rom. 10. 15.</note> die in Infancy, ſeeing by outward means they cannot come to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, till they be able to hear, and may not be judged within the Covenant nor baptized, till they manifeſt faith: ſure according to his opinion, to our notion they are all debarred Heaven at a blow.</p>
               <p>But truly, as the opinion is, ſo is the conſequences that attend it, erroneous and falſe: but in as much as this ſtone is much ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at by ſome of that way, I ſhall indeavour to remove it, in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Doctrine of Infants Baptiſme agreeth fully with the Word of God. The Infants of the faithfull being within the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace externally, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7. <hi>That this Covenant is to a thouſand Generations,</hi> Pſal. 105. 8. <hi>That God is not the God of the Jews only, but of the Gentiles,</hi> Rom. 4. 29. <hi>That the Gentiles are fellow heires of the ſame body, and partakers of the promiſe in Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 3. 6. <hi>That there is no</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>difference, but that he that is Lord of all, is rich to all,</hi> Rom. 10. 12. His grace and mercy being not leſſened, but inlarged, <hi>All his promiſes of grace being to the Gentiles, yea and amen in Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 24. <note place="margin">Act. 15. 18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Touching inward Sanctity, and inward right in the Covenant, as it is Gods worke and intereſſing of whom it pleaſeth him, ſo it is only known to him, <hi>To whom all his works are known from the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 22. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>foundation of the World;</hi> A thing not within our Spheare; wee being to <hi>meddle with things revealed,</hi> and to proceed according to that.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this Covenant of grace externally, of which we treat; it is extended more largely then according to <hi>J. S.</hi> his narrow <note place="margin">Deu. 29. 29.</note> minding of it, that ſeemeth as if he would thruſt himſelfe into the room of God, medling with things ſecret, and proceeding in his meaſuring of things that way, making the Covenant of grace externally to be with the inviſible Elect, <hi>and not with the called in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of whom <hi>many are called but few choſen;</hi> ſo as he is not able I am ſure as infallible to ſhew one perſon of that Covenant)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123379:13"/> whereas it is and may be known that the Covenant of grace is made with Chriſts Kingdome, his Church, and that conſiſts of <hi>Virgins, five wiſe, and five fooliſh;</hi> and <hi>Iſrael though as the ſand of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Sea, yet but a remnant ſhall be ſaved.</hi> If <hi>J. S.</hi> would but be pleaſed to <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 27.</note> take notice of the outwardneſſe of the Covenant of grace as before, as well as the inwardneſſe of it; the outwardneſſe of the matter to which the Covenant is made, as well as the inwardneſſe of the matter <hi>known only to God,</hi> he would ſurely be of another minde, and would not ſay, <hi>it croſſeth the Word of God to hold children within the Covenant of Grace,</hi> for truly if they be not neither inwardly nor outwardly in the ſame, they are in a ſad caſe, being wonderfull loſers by the comming of Chriſt into the world <hi>with grace and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 1. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>truth,</hi> by whom ſo many gaine: But it is evident by what before is declared, that they are in that Covenant, and ſo are to be ſealed as others, with the Seale of it, and that ſo doing is fully according to the Word of God.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith he, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt affirmes, that all are conceived in ſinne, children of wrath, and under the curſe, ſo as they cannot ſee the Kingdome</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Groſſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> 
                  <hi>of God unleſſe born again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I ſay, <hi>Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> heires of the promiſe were borne in ſinne, and yet in the Covenant of grace, ſo ſoon and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were born: <hi>J. S.</hi> is yet beſide the matter and much to ſeeke.</p>
               <p>A little to unfold this matter ſo hidden to <hi>J. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way: There is a different conſideration to be had of this matter, even as there is of a perſon of yeeres, who may truly bee ſaid to be a Saint and alſo a ſinner in a different ſenſe. So the infants of the faithfull may be ſaid to be born in ſin and brought forth in iniquity, and ſo in that conſideration under wrath; and yet in another minding, born the holy ſeed of promiſe, even as <hi>Iſaack</hi> and the Iſraelites of old, as witneſſeth the Apoſtle, <hi>ye are the Children of the promiſe;</hi> and again, <hi>the promiſe is to you and your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 3. 25. Act. 2. 19.</note> let it but be conſidered in the caſe of <hi>Iſaack</hi> in particular, who was in a ſpeciall manner the childe of promiſe, yet he was born in ſinne, &amp;c. Let <hi>J. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way uſe their wit and reaſon; in ſtead of faith, to find out this matter ſome other way, and they ſhall but tire themſelves in vain: It will appeare a truth fully held forth in the holy Scriptures, that though all men ſince their fall in <hi>Adam</hi> (Chriſt the new or ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> excepted) have
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123379:13"/> been, and are born in ſinne, and ſo under wrath that way; yet a number have obtained ſuch free grace, as that (though in another conſideration) they are and have been by generation the ſeed of promiſe, holy, and ſuch as God hath and doth owne for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, even as hee did <hi>Iſaack</hi> and the ſeed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, and the ſeed of the beleeving Gentiles, who are under mercie and grace by promiſe, as they are under ſinne and wrath the other way: And were and are high in the account of God, what ever meane account <hi>J. S.</hi> hath of them; of all which, and who, and what to beleeve, let the upright heart to God judge, as <hi>J. S.</hi> in the end of his Reaſon ſetteth down, thinking belike he had ſaid ſomething that had concluded all.</p>
               <p>But alas, how farre theſe weak and inconſiderate reaſons are from effecting what the Author of them intendeth, any one that is not of a very childiſh underſtanding may be able to diſcerne: for ſure men muſt be childiſh indeed, that in a matter of ſuch weight and concernment as is their outward Chriſtianity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Chriſt that way, ſhall by ſuch reaſons be ſo ſwayed, as to renounce and reject the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Containing a diſcovery of the vaine pretence of</hi> J. S. <hi>of finding Baptiſme now loſt and fallen out of the world, as hee holdeth, in the holy Scriptures of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I. S. At the end of pag. 37. ſaith, <hi>That the ſubſtance of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſcourſe had been about the ſubjects of Baptiſme,</hi> in which (if any pleaſe to beleeve his own witneſſe in his owne cauſe) <hi>hee hath diſproved the Baptiſme of two ſorts of perſons; Firſt, of beleevers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants; Secondly, the Baptiſme in the defection of Antichriſt, being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme in infancie alſo:</hi> So as like a work-man indeed he hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown the outward Chriſtianity, and relation to Chriſt that way, priviledges of grace, and Saintſhip, and what not; all which are of much concernment every manner of way, unto men; and that of all perſons in the world, onely thoſe few; ſo of late baptized
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123379:14"/> by totall dipping: Is not this <hi>Goliah</hi> like, and can any marvell that we poore <hi>Iſraelites</hi> thus ſtripped and left naked, are offended and complain, being ſuch loſers, and turned out of all? Had he any great reaſon to complain as he doth in his Epiſtle, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in his book again and againe, as pag. 40. <hi>Some have ſo wide mouthes open againſt them that wiſhed them ever well:</hi> Well indeed, to unchriſtian them, and to ſtrip them of all relation to Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally, quit them of all intereſt in the Covenant of God, yea making them <hi>as without God in the world, ſo caſting them out, that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 12. 1 Sam. 26. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>they may goe and ſerve other gods:</hi> And can he think much that they complaine of wrong: What have they more? <hi>He ſaith he will leave them to God, to whom they muſt be accomptable for all their hard words:</hi> But what are thoſe hard words; ſurely ſuch as theſe, that they ſay their way and courſe is erroneous, a new invention, having evill conſequences attending of it; that they are light and mutable in their courſes, and very cenſorious; and is all this ſo great a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and hard to be born: Are not his words, or thoſe of his way farre more eaſie, that condemns all the people and ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt in the world for unbaptized; the courſe and way of all Churches, reformed or ſeparate, as Idolatrous and not of God, only thoſe of his way excepted; though the ſaid perſons or Churches be endued with never ſo lively graces, and walk ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſincerely and uprightly with good conſcience in the way God hath made known to them: But, ſaith he, <hi>I leave them to God, to whom they ſhall give account for all their hard words:</hi> Surely he forgetteth, and doth not think of the hard cenſures and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous condemnations, that he, and thoſe of his way give and lay upon all that follow not their erroneous way and courſe.</p>
               <p>In way of further complaint, he ſaith, <hi>Men doe as the Tyrants did of old:</hi> And old ſtory indeed, and ill applyed, <hi>but though he be not, he ſaith certain of the truth of it, he is certain that ſome are little better minded, that labour to cover the godly with ſuch filth as they vomit out of their ſelf-ſick ſtomacks:</hi> To all which I ſay its more eaſie to ſee a moat in anothers eye, then a beam in their own; how doth <hi>J. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way cover the godly, and the Churches of Chriſt with the filth of their vomit which they caſt forth, and yet he wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his mouth as innocent, and wonderfully as we ſee complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of others, that have more cauſe to complaine of him, for he can lay heavie burthens and grievous to be born, making men no
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123379:14"/> Chriſtiant, no Churches of Chriſt, but Synagogues of Satan, of the world, Antichriſtians, Idolaters, and what not; all which men muſt bear, though never ſo innocent: but now the leaſt of theſe he will not indure to touch with his finger, but he cryeth out bitterly; but as their dealing is unequall in this, even ſo it is in other things. But now to return and leave this digreſſion.</p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 38. he telleth us, <hi>That this falling out ſo:</hi> How is that? That that the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of all perſons and Churches in the world (thoſe few of his way excepted) <hi>being void and null,</hi> an Idoll, and none of Chriſts. <hi>It followeth, ſaith he, that we are now to ſeek for the Lords true Baptiſme.</hi> This is ſure a wonderfull caſe indeed, that the Baptiſme of Chriſt ſhould be thus loſt, and fallen out of the world. Now, ſaith he, in <hi>a caſe ſo difficult as ſome would make it, two things in ſpeciall are to be inquired into: Firſt, How, or where to finde it. Secondly, how it may be obtained, being found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt: <hi>If any Ordinance be ſo deceaſed and loſt, as we do not know where it is afoot in Gods way in the world:</hi> (a rare caſe) Baptiſme is thus loſt and deceaſed in his opinion) ſo as thoſe that find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unbaptized, may be made partakers of it. What are they to do? <hi>They are to go to Chriſt and his Apoſtles as the godly then did.</hi> But I ſay Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles have left the world, and are in heaven: I but, ſaith he, <hi>That is to the Scriptures, which are the lively Oracles of God. Anſ.</hi> And ſo they were when Chriſt and the Apoſtles were on the earth. <hi>The ſpirit, ſaith he, ſpeaking in them to a beleever. Anſw.</hi> They ſtand in the place of Chriſt for advice and counſell, and ſo they did then, for both our Lord and the Apoſtles ſent us to them, and ſpake nothing but according to them. But what of this? Truly nothing to the purpoſe, nor yet that which is added: Namely, <hi>That they have ability to furniſh a man of faith with all truth, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures quoted, compared together, will prove.</hi> To which, I ſay, they do eaſily and fully prove the ſame, and there were never any that held the perfection of the Scriptures, that did deny the ſame: yet is <hi>J. S.</hi> never the nearer for all his pains in multiplying expreſſions to make the matter ſeem ſomething; when indeed it is nothing at all to purpoſe: For, <hi>To the Law and the Teſtimony we are to go:</hi> And in <note place="margin">Eſay 8. 20. 2 Pet. 1, 19.</note> difficult caſes, <hi>To take heed to the Word, as to a Light that enlighteneth in darkneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now firſt, I ſay, the Scripture giveth no light at all concerning ſuch a ceſſation of the Church and Ordinances: Nay, it is againſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123379:15"/> the light of the Scriptures to beleeve any ſuch thing, Jeſus Chriſt having ſaid, <hi>That hell gates ſhall not prevail againſt his Church;</hi> and <note place="margin">Matth. 16. Matth. 28. 20.</note> having alſo <hi>promiſed his preſence for preſervation and continuation for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſay, it is but <hi>directively,</hi> that the Scriptures do <hi>furniſh men</hi> in all caſes; now their direction in this caſe, it is to the Church, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 17, 18.</note> and to the miniſtery of man, for the enjoying, and being made partakers of the holy Ordinances of God.</p>
               <p>The holy Scriptures of old in a like manner ſtood in the ſtead of <hi>Moſes and the Prophets</hi> in a ſenſe: And yet the heathen were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to Jeruſalem for the Ordinances as they did; and did not act <note place="margin">Eſay 8. 20. 2 Pet. 1. 19. 2 Chro. 6. 32.</note> them themſelves with the help of the Law: The Scriptures in a ſenſe ſtood in the ſtead of Chriſt and the Apoſtles; yet the people muſt go to <hi>John;</hi> yea, our Lord himſelf, that he might <hi>fulfill righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 3. 15.</note> muſt go to him: <hi>Cornelius</hi> muſt ſend for <hi>Peter; Paul</hi> muſt <note place="margin">Act. 10. 32. Act. 9. 10.</note> have <hi>Ananias;</hi> and ſo ſuch as attain the knowledge of the truth, they are to go to the Church and Miniſtery of man, appointed of God; and ſo that way to be <hi>added to the Church,</hi> and made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the holy Ordinances of God: for it is moſt certain, the <note place="margin">Act. 2. 47.</note> Scriptures act nothing, neither can they: they onely direct in <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note> their directions is always as aforeſaid, and no otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I ſay, it is not true that the Scriptures are in the ſtead of the holy Miniſtery, ordained by God: The Scriptures were not in the ſtead of the Prieſts, in caſe of <hi>Sauls ſacrificing,</hi> nor in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzia</hi> the King his burning <hi>incenſe,</hi> to inable them to do as they did: <note place="margin">1 Sam. 13. 12.</note> The Scriptures were not in ſtead of <hi>circumciſed Jews</hi> unto the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to inable them, or make them capable of <hi>building the Temple:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 26. 17, 18.</note> They were not in ſtead of <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> to our Lord: They were not in ſtead of <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his friends. As it is not in ſtead of <note place="margin">Ezra 4. 3. Matth. 3. 15. Acts 10. 32.</note> Chriſt, the Apoſtles, or holy Miniſtery to an unbaptized perſon or perſons to inable them warrantably to Baptize, and ſo without Commiſſion to raiſe this Ordinance a new, ſo loſt and deceaſed out of the world, according to his opinion.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures which he quoteth, I ſhall ſet down, and they are theſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 25, &amp;c. Now I appeal to the indifferent Reader whether theſe Scriptures, all, or any of them, are any other then directive.</p>
               <p>Again, whether their direction, it be not to a precedent Stative Church, and miniſtery of man, appointed by God, as formerly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123379:15"/> under <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets; ſo in this latter diſpenſation, under Chriſt and the Apoſtles, as is before declared.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, whether theſe Scriptures, or any of theſe, or all of theſe, compared together, do give direction to a perſon unbaptized him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to baptize either himſelf or others: and whether they do not rather teſtifie againſt ſuch uſurpation of Gods holy things, and <hi>running before they be ſent,</hi> in thus doing a thing that <hi>never came into</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jerem. 23. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>the minde of God, much leſſe did he require it at their hands:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jerem. 32. 35.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. S.</hi> proceedeth, and ſaith, <hi>By all which we ſee, that all things are contained in the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, in the way of direction, and therefore ſuch practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are without the direction of the Scripture, are unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſuch as is their caſting away as Null their preſent Baptiſme, becauſe of ſome corruptions that did attend it; and beginning it again with greater corruptions; namely, by an unbaptized perſon, without Commiſſion, acting of it.</p>
               <p>Here he addeth many good words in commendation of the Scriptures; <hi>As containing all things concerning faith and obedience, as being the Propheticall mouth of Chriſt, to which all muſt repair unto; and all Doctrines and practices muſt be tryed by; and an Angell from heaven is not to be beleeved, but as they ſpeak according to it.</hi> All which is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, as I ſaid before: And what then? Truly nothing: Though he go over the ſame matter again, with ſome different expreſſions: and ſome of them improper; carrying a ſhew of favouring his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and what he would have: As where he ſaith, <hi>The Scriptures is the onely place:</hi> How is this proper, or true, unleſſe he mean in a directive way? <hi>Where any Ordinance of God, in caſe aforeſaid,</hi> that is, of ceſſation, and loſſe of being again, <hi>when, or whereſoever any of theſe (meaning)</hi> Ordinances of God, <hi>cannot be found:</hi> (What then?) We are, ſaith he, <hi>to go to the Scriptures directly, and recover the ſame again, as</hi> Cant. 1. 7. Eſay 8. 19, 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All this is but the ſame over again, we are to go to the Scripture for direction, (if the caſe were ſo) the Scripture direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not acting, as <hi>Eſay</hi> 8. 19, 20. the Church acting accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that direction, and therefore perſons are ſent thither, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 7. alleadged, which is according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Scripture, which alwayes ſendeth men to the Church in ſuch caſes: ſo as in this copiouſneſſe, he doth but puzzle his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to make him beleeve what he is never able to prove.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:123379:16"/>
               <p>He proceedeth, ſaying: <hi>Thus having found out the place or ſubject,</hi> (very improper expreſſions) Is not the Scripture the ground and foundation of all Ordinances in a directive way? Did ever any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian queſtion it, much leſſe deny it? That he ſhould with often going over the ſame, and with ſuch improper expreſſions, and far fetches ſeek to make it appear as a diſcovery of truth not known, or at leaſt not aſſented unto: ſure he had ſome further drift in it then ordinary.</p>
               <p>In the next place he ſaith; <hi>It is to be known how they that want it may come orderly by it; For, ſaith he, though God hath joyned his Word and Ordinances together, yet he hath injoyned an orderly way for his people to come to injoy them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I would fain know to what end all the former matter ſerveth, if ſo be God require an orderly way: for, as I ſaid before, there is none that deny the Scriptures, in a directive way, to be the ground and foundation of all Ordinances. <hi>J. S.</hi> might have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his labour, for it was to as much purpoſe as for a man to prove there is a Sun in the firmament; which all grant.</p>
               <p>In this it had been far better for him to have made full diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, how they that (in ſuch a caſe) want it, may come orderly by it; in as much as God requireth this. And ſurely, if God require an orderly way, <hi>J. S.</hi> and others of his way, will yet remain in a great ſtrait; and will finde it a matter more eaſie to caſt away an Ordinance (as they have done their Baptiſme) for the diſorder and corruption that did attend it then in an orderly way to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ſame again: for certainly, the Scriptures, according to what before is ſet forth, direct to a precedent Church, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of man, ordained of God, and ſent as <hi>John</hi> was: <hi>And if not a Chriſt, a</hi> Moſes, <hi>or</hi> Elias, <hi>or Prophet from heaven,</hi> the blinde Jews could <note place="margin">John 1. 25.</note> ſee it to be unlawfull for any other.</p>
               <p>How will he do now? He is but where he was, an orderly way according to God is neceſſary; there being no gathered Church to be found remaining, no, not baptized perſons to be found, nor any Prophets ſent from God, according as his judgement is: What will he do, or what courſe will he preſcribe? He conceiveth <hi>this orderly way is onely in and hy the Church</hi> (I had thought he would have rather ſaid in the Scriptures, for to me it ſeemeth he hath unſaid all he ſaid before) <hi>wherein is the power of Chriſt, he ſaith, to ſet on foot his Ordinances:</hi> So, as it ſeemeth, now it is not in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:123379:16"/> (as before he indeavoured to make his Reader believe.) But in the Church of God, ſo as we are not, as he ſaid before, to go directly to the Scriptures, but we are to go to the Church of God. But now this is the caſe with <hi>J. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way, there is no Church remaining in the world to be found, how then will he do? to help now at a dead lift, they will make a Church, that they may make Ordinances anew, and be the ſpouſe of Chriſt whether he will or no, I ſuppoſe greater arrogancy cannot be ſhewed in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> But let us ſee how they will do it, thus ſaith he, <hi>When God is pleaſed to take a people to himſelf, and by the power of his truth to unite them to his Son, and ſo in an orderly hody among themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now this ſuppoſed orderly gathered Church, pretended (after the manner of the Church of <hi>Rome)</hi> to be Gods: conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of perſons unbaptized. Now I would hear minde <hi>J. S.</hi> of his firſt Argument againſt Infants Baptiſme; namely, that which hath neither precept nor example in Scripture is unlawfull; let him or any of his way ſhew an example of a unbaptized Church, ſince Baptiſme was on foot in the World, or any command from God for perſons unbaptized <hi>to congregate and aſſume,</hi> for ſo he after ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>to become a Church,</hi> indeed it may be ſaid preſume, for it is without all doubt, great preſumption, and a doing that God never ſpake to any to do, but the contrary, namely, to repaire to the Church before gathered, and by him made partakers of his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in a right way, there to be added and made partakers of the Ordinances with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. S.</hi> ſaith further, <hi>When it pleaſed God to take a people to himſelf, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> When God is pleaſed to take a people to himſelf in ſuch a way, there alwaies was new diſcoveries of his will, new grants of favour, there were new ſignes and miracles, there were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and men ſent immediately to declare his good pleaſure: as appeareth firſt in the caſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> after in the example of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and that people: and laſt of all in the caſe of <hi>Chriſt and the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen: 15. 17, 18. Exod. 19. 16. Heb. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> when not the Jewes only, but the Gentiles, were drawn to God, <hi>By ſignes and miracles and divers gifts,</hi> he gave confirmation to his pleaſure, as of old he had done.</p>
               <p>But alas, here is no ſuch thing attending this ſuppoſed gathering of ſuch people to God, for indeed the gathering is of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and anſwerable to Gods gathering of his people in ſome other caſes more ordinary. As namely, his gathering of them out of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123379:17"/> 
                  <hi>captivity of old,</hi> when they were in <hi>Babylon,</hi> or his gathering them out of <hi>apoſtacy and defection,</hi> under <hi>Jeroboam</hi> or the like: figures of this ſpirituall captivity and apoſtacy of <hi>Babylon</hi> now. But as then there were no new beginnings of Ordinances, no new Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor any ſignes or miracles for confirmation of their returne and gathering to the Lord: Even ſo the caſe being a like, there is no new beginnings of Church and Baptiſme, which would require as heretofore, ſuch like confirmation. And certainly, if the return and gathering of Gods people to himſelf, were any other then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe gatherings from captivity and apoſtacy of old, I ſay, ſurely if there were ſuch a new taking of people, and raiſing of them as is pretended, God would have manifeſted his pleaſure as of old, <hi>by ſignes and miracles,</hi> or at leaſt by perſons ſent from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the buſineſſe, as <hi>John</hi> was.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. S.</hi> further ſaith, <hi>Such a people ſo gathered and conſtituted, have right to all the priviledges ordained and appointed by God for their mutuall comfort and well-being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Juſt as <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his friends had, or might have had, in the like caſe, without <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe Miniſtery they muſt make uſe of, he being authorized of God to the worke, and they directed of God to him, and not bidden to do it themſelves.</p>
               <p>Now this he pretendeth to prove from certain Scriptures, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 21. 22, 23. <hi>Anſw.</hi> For that in the <hi>Romans</hi> it is marvellous he ſhould think that to be a proof: I ſay firſt, that was ſpoken of the Church of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that were gathered by Chriſt, and waſhed with his waſhing in an orderly way, by ſuch as were not only baptized, but had authority to baptize others, they were Gods Church indeed, of whom glorious things are ſpoken. But what is this to perſons unbaptized, pretending to be a Church, and to be gathered by God, when they cannot ſhew the leaſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for it.</p>
               <p>Againe, it ſpeaketh of heirs, now may heires, becauſe heires, and ſo every heire of Chriſt, act Ordinances of ſo high a nature, becauſe heires; ſure they, as obedient children muſt ſerve God in an orderly way, and not in ſuch a confuſed courſe, as that upon the pretence of heirſhip, young as well as old, yea, women alſo might do it, for <hi>They are all one in Chriſt.</hi> Nay, which is more, though unbaptized, and ſo the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> or <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his friends, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 28.</note> not <hi>Philip</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> but might have done it themſelves. I ſuppoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:123379:17"/> this Scripture, any one that hath but common reaſon in him, will ſee it is to no purpoſe at all.</p>
               <p>But that other happily may ſtand him in ſtead, and the ſcope of that is to declare the intereſt of Chriſts Church to all things, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures direction, alwaies provided. And what then? then people may make themſelves the Church of Chriſt, or pretend at leaſt ſo to be: and then they are ſo intereſſed forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in all things. The <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church can make as large claim as they in this matter, and ſpeak as much for themſelves: ſurely, if perſons in earthly caſes could do the like, there would not be a few found in ſuch claimes and pretences, but they would by wiſe men, be thought ſitter for <hi>Bedlam</hi> then any place elſe. In further anſwer, I ſay, that was ſpoken of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and ſo is true of all other Churches, gathered and inſtated by Chriſt in an order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way, by ſuch means and inſtruments as had authority from him. But what is this to perſons that want this jnſtating, by ſuch inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſuch a way: Truly no more then it could for thoſe that <hi>called themſelves Jewes and were not,</hi> or then it would have availed <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 9.</note> the Heathen of old, to have injoyed the priviledges with the <hi>Jewes</hi> in Gods holy things, in particular, of building the Temple, to whom it was told, <hi>it was not for them to build, &amp;c.</hi> It cannot be imagined, that ſuch large priviledges ſhould, according to due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <note place="margin">Eſr. 4. 3.</note> appertain to ſuch; the Scripture being wholly ſilent concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their right: It is but uſurpation for ſuch to challenge ſuch a condition, of being called to be Chriſts Church, as it was in them that ſaid, <hi>they were Apoſtles, and were not,</hi> as theſe in like kinde are <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 2.</note> not the Churches of Chriſt, rightly gathered and conſtituted, whatever they pretend to be; I ſuppoſe it will alſo appear to the Reader, that this Scripture ſerveth nothing at all to purpoſe in the matter in hand.</p>
               <p>But <hi>J. S.</hi> ſuppoſing to have made ſome proofe in the aforeſaid matter, ſaith, <hi>that by vertue of this union they have with their head Chriſt, the body thus joyntly conſidered, hath the power and authority of Chriſt within themſelves, to chuſe or make uſe of any one or more of her members, as occaſioa offers, to adminiſter Baptiſme upon the whole body, and ſo upon themſelves in the firſt place as a part of the ſame:</hi> This is the great concluſion drawn from the former premiſes; but it is onely ſaid; for alas, that before is no proofe at all of the matter; what precept or example is there in the Scripture for the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123379:18"/> of this, certainly none at all, for this is unwritten tradition; and I dare ſay, as pure popery as any can be: for men thus to faine caſes, and then to give authority in ſuch caſes as the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is altogether ſilent in.</p>
               <p>But ſaith he further, if any pleaſe to take his word for it, <hi>ſuch may be as truly ſaid to be ſent and authorized by Chriſt (thus as of old, by Chriſt in his humane body; even ſo now in his divine and ſpirituall body:</hi> that is, <hi>this unbaptized company pretending to be a Church:</hi> Now I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell whether there be any ſo ſimple as to beleeve ſuch doctrine as this; that a company of unbaptized perſons are Chriſts divine and ſpirituall body; and that ſo, as what they order perſons to doe in the matter of ordinances in particular of Baptiſme, though it doe not concurre with the Scriptures; is as true and reall a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and as full authority as the holy Apoſtles had that were ſent of Chriſt himſelfe; and beſide, that ſuch high termes of divine and ſpirituall ſhould be proper to this fained body; and onely the term humane, ſhould belong to Chriſts perſon, when he was manifeſt in the world; it is ſure very much; and at leaſt ſheweth plainly how wonderfully hee is conceited of his owne <hi>Idea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſtrange doctrine he will prove by a reaſon thus; <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a Church doth riſe in her true conſtitution:</hi> I aske from whence is this riſing, from the bottomleſſe pit: I never heard of <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 19. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>but comming down from heaven:</hi> But <hi>Babylon,</hi> and this little Teret of it, may riſe happily from the earth. Againe, <hi>in her true conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> I ſay, it is likely to be a very true conſtitution without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. There he ſaith, <hi>are her ordinances;</hi> Yes, but in an orderly way they muſt be acted; it is not for <hi>Saul</hi> to ſacrifice: But ſaith he, <hi>there is power alſo to adminiſter the ſame:</hi> but ſure, not without right or lawfull inſtruments, <hi>God is the God of Order.</hi> But the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 37.</note> reaſon that killeth all dead before it, and concludeth the matter fully, is this, <hi>That where a thing is wanting, there muſt be of neceſſity a beginning to reduce the thing again into being;</hi> this is the concluſion of all. And is not <hi>J. S.</hi> come to a faire Haven after his ſore tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell and great hazzard. Neceſſity hath no law. But where is that due order, <hi>and orderly way of ſeeking of God</hi> which he before ſpake of? Truly it is a ſad caſe, that any by their erroneous judgement and following their own way, ſhould bring themſelves into ſuch a ſnare or ſtraight, and then plead neceſſity to doe that which is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:123379:18"/> not lawfull for them, and think neceſſity will beare them out. Diſobedient <hi>Saul,</hi> by his evill courſe, had brought himſelfe into a great ſtraight, whereupon he adventured to doe that which did <note place="margin">1 Sam. 13. 12.</note> not appertain to him to doe; but for all he pleaded neceſſity it would not ſerve his turne, for he was told by the Prophet from the Lord, <hi>That hee had done fooliſhly, and that to obey was better then ſacrifice.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">v. 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus ſaith he, <hi>I have ſhewed my judgement, that if Baptiſme be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting where it is to be had, namely in the holy Scriptures.</hi> Secondly, <hi>how from thence to be obtained, by Gods calling an</hi> unbaptized <hi>people into an holy fellowſhip with Chriſt, from whom (though unbaptized) they have power to aſſume as a Church; ſo the Ordinance of Baptiſme upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now courteous Reader, this is the ſum of the matter, conſider of it, and ſee if it be not a faire judgement and well grounded, and whether thou canſt judge this to be any other then Popiſh divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, which the Romaniſt can ſay in the like kind for their courſe; for cannot they ſay as much for making Chriſts reall body in the Euchariſt, by <hi>hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> as theſe can ſay for making his divine and ſpirituall body, as they call it; for they pretend the Scriptures as theſe doe, they aſſume to themſelves ſuch a ſtate, to be Chriſts Church; and to have ſuch power in what they doe, even as theſe doe; but truly, as theirs is onely pretended, and not reall; Even ſo in like is this, meerely faigned and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>But he ſaith, <hi>he will cleare up this matter;</hi> (Indeed it needs clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, for it is yet very dark and ſmoakie) this hee will doe, <hi>by ſhewing the manner of the aforeſaid Conſtitution in the cauſes of it:</hi> How will he doe it? in <hi>pag.</hi> 40. by ſaying over again what he had ſaid again and again before; namely, <hi>that the Scriptures, remaining in the place of the Apoſtles for us to have recourſe unto, and ſerve as the mouth of Chriſt:</hi> Alas this is but a poore clearing, for this is onely in a directive way, as before I noted. And what then? The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures being ſo; truly nothing at all. Yes, ſaith he, <hi>as the Apoſtles did before the Scriptures were written;</hi> To which I ſay, there were Scriptures before the Apoſtles, to which the Apoſtles had an eye and regard, and directed others to doe the like: The holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles they acted Ordinances of Religion <hi>preaching, breaking bread, and baptizing.</hi> The Scripture acts nothing, neither can they: ſurely <note place="margin">Act. 2. 42.</note>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:123379:19"/> this is a poore clearing; we will minde the Scriptures hee here quoteth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 20. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 19. 20, 21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 6, 7, 8. In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I will not tire my ſelfe and the Reader; certainly no man can imagine any thing more then direction from that full and perfect rule of the Scriptures, as gatherable from thoſe places of Scripture, which as before I ſaid none deny, let him but call to mind what he ſaid of an orderly way which God requireth, and how that is as he conceiveth by the Church; and then let him tell mee if hee can to what purpoſe theſe Scriptures are, or that which followeth; <hi>that as the Lords people conferred with the Prophets and Apoſtles about their great affaires, ſo have the Lords people now, Moſes and the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles in their writings, as</hi> Luk. 16. 29. And what then, truly nothing (it is but for direction as before) nor yet that which further followeth in this clearing matter of the conſtituting cauſes; which are, ſaith he, <hi>with the ſpirit of life in them, as effectuall as their perſonall preſence, if not more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Stay a while, the matter is ſure otherwiſe, for this effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuallneſſe, if it were granted, is but directive. But it is not wholly granted, for that the Apoſtles were men inſpired and ſent of God to declare his will, they were a ſaving meanes of good to men; and God in his good pleaſure, as a double mercy, gave his Word, and ſent his Apoſtles and Prophets; ſure I take it, it muſt needs follow, that if the Scriptures were as effectuall without the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles (and rather more) then with them; then God gave the Apoſtles in vaine, and the Churches were great loſers by their perſonall preſence; but the truth is otherwiſe, as is moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: The Scripture (with the Spirit of life in them) act no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but onely direct and furniſh men how to act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God, in an orderly way, according to what hee holdeth.</p>
               <p>For proofe of what before he affirmed of the effectualneſſe of the Scripture, he quoteth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 62. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18, 19. <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 3, 5, 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That in <hi>John,</hi> ſpeaketh of Chriſt aſcending where he was before, how this ſhould prove any thing is beyond my thoughts, I will ſay nothing, but leave the Reader to judge of it. That place of <hi>Peter</hi> is of the ſure direction of the Word in dark, and our doing well to take heed to it. That in the <hi>Revelation</hi> is of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:123379:19"/> the two witneſſes; a thing too myſterious to be a proofe in this caſe.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe <hi>J. S.</hi> will not hold himſelfe to be one of thoſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, nor he, with others of his way, to be both thoſe witneſſes there ſpoken of. I will ſay no more but leave the Reader to judge whether theſe Scriptures doe prove that the holy Scriptures with the Spirit of life in them (as he is pleaſed to ſay) are in ſtead of the Apoſtles perſonally ſent of God with power to act ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; or whether they in the caſe of the Ordinances diſpenſing in an orderly way, are as much or more effectuall then the Apoſtles perſonally that were ſent of Chriſt for that end, who did not ſend the Scriptures, as in the caſe of the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> but <hi>Philip;</hi> and in the caſe of <hi>Cornelius, Peter,</hi> as in thoſe and the like inſtances may be ſeen.</p>
               <p>He proceedeth, and in full concluding of this matter, ſaith, and <hi>thus all ſucceſſion</hi> (what phraſe have we here) <hi>from the beginning came to Chriſt.</hi> (Of what ſpeakes hee now, of Ordinances?) I had thought all Ordinances had ever proceeded from him, he being ever the Lord of the Church, and ſure he meaneth the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; namely, thoſe ordained of old under <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets;</hi> theſe laſted &amp; continued to the coming of Chriſt into the world, the ſubſtance indeed of thoſe ſhadows; ſo his ſenſe may be good. <hi>From Chriſt,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>to the Apoſtles; from the Apoſtles to the Scriptures:</hi> This is pure non-ſenſe, if I miſtake not; and beſide, I aske him where is that orderly way he told us of, and how is the caſe now according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>by him alleadged for the Authority of an unbaptized Church;</hi> Doth he not by this diſcent ſeclude them from all, rather then inright them to any ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorite; happily he will ſay, <hi>Oh from the Scriptures to us;</hi> very good: But firſt, how from Chriſt to the Apoſtles? Did Chriſt our Lord preferre the Apoſtles before his beloved Spouſe for whom he gave himſelfe? I alwayes took the Apoſtles <hi>as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Church for Chriſts ſake.</hi> Secondly, did the Ordinances <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 5.</note> proceed from Chriſt to the perſons of the Apoſtles; or to their office as Apoſtles; So as when they in regard either of perſon or office left the world, it deſcended to the Scripture; certainly, the right and intereſt of the Scriptures was the ſame before the death and ceſſation of the Apoſtles as after; and the Scriptures gained no legacie by ſuch friends, unleſſe a ſealing to the truth and full
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:123379:20"/> authority of their direction: <hi>ſo from the Scriptures to us:</hi> a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full matter, a very fair Ring, from the Scriptures to the Scriptures, and ſo to us, juſt nothing but a ſhew of words without matter.</p>
               <p>Further he ſaith, <hi>That all ſucceſſion is now ſpirituall:</hi> So it ſeemeth he holdeth it was carnall before, when it was from <hi>Abraham to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, from Moſes to Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and ſo to the Scriptures;</hi> and now it is from the Scriptures to us, it is ſpirituall; a rare conceit. He ſaith, <hi>it is now according to faith;</hi> whether he mean faith of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, or what elſe, is hard to ſay; but it mattereth not much, for he is beſide the Scriptures, and walking in ſome other field. <hi>It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not, ſaith he, the perſonall ſucceſſion of any, but onely the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sure <hi>J. S.</hi> ſpeaketh in a ſtrange tongue, he is never able to make out his ſenſe, that ſucceſſion follows the Word, the Word being immoveable, and that which abideth for ever, and hath no place for ſucceſſion, though he thus ſpeaketh he know not what. And <hi>the word of God, he ſaith, giveth being to all Order and Ordinances:</hi> It doth give being of direction and warrant, declaring what is good and lawfull, and what not: It acts nothing: <hi>God requireth an orderly way, and that is by the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, courteous Reader, do but ſeriouſly conſider how <hi>J. S.</hi> hath cleared the way of raiſing and beginning again Baptiſme loſt and fallen out of the world, <hi>as he beleeveth:</hi> and how he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the difficulties in the way, which he <hi>ealleth clouds that darken the skie:</hi> See if thou do not yet finde it very dark and cloudy as ever, and never the clearer for all the labour and pains he hath taken; and whether his labour and travell herein hath been to any more purpoſe then the waſhing of the Blackmoore.</p>
               <p>For firſt of all: <hi>Whereas he referreth thee to the Scriptures, as the Succeſſours of the Apoſtles in his opinion:</hi> Firſt, Thou ſeeſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were before the Apoſtles, and the Apoſtles themſelves were guided by them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the Scriptures are onely directive, and act no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, neither can they: and beſide, they do not direct to any ſuch courſe as the conſtituting an unbaptized Church, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizing unbaptized perſons to baptize.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Thou ſeeſt what great cauſe of doubt and queſtion there is, according to his opinion, whether theſe Scriptures be the Scriptures of God, and whether they have not loſt their being,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:123379:20"/> having been ſo long in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and in the hands of Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; eſpecially if it be minded that they were by Antichriſtians tranſlated into our native Tongue: their tranſlating muſt needs make them Antichriſtian, and to be rejected as falſe, as well as their Baptiſme. Where will <hi>J. S.</hi> be then (do thou but think) for the raiſing a new his Church and Baptiſme, which I would wiſh him and thoſe of his way to conſider of well.</p>
               <p>But then in the ſecond place; <hi>God being to be ſought as he holdeth in an orderly way, according to what he hath declared as his judgement, and this orderly way being by the Church rightly gathered and conſtituted, to whom Chriſt hath committed the power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider, good Reader, in the firſt place, that if the Scriptures be not Antichriſtian, (as his opinion inforceth) that they have in them no ground or warrant by any example or precept for ſuch an unbaptized Church, neither can ſuch a ſuppoſed Church be orderly conſtituted, or the proceed thereof orderly, the Scripture being wholly ſilent concerning any ſuch thing: This conceit of ſo making Chriſts Church, and ſo making Baptiſme; being a meer Popiſh Tenent, and the proceed therin like unto theirs in ſuch like caſes: So as this Ordinance of Chriſts Baptiſme, being, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his opinion, deſtroyed in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and there being no orderly Church of Chriſt in earth to be found, as he holdeth: nor no <hi>Chriſt, Moſes, Eliah, or Prophet from heaven appearing:</hi> nor yet any that by <hi>Signes and Miracles</hi> can prove the truth of their <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> I conceive it neceſſarily followeth, and I willingly leave all men free to judge of it. That <hi>J. S.</hi> is yet, for all his clearing, in a great ſtraight, and under a dark cloud; out of, and from under which, he will not be able to get, unleſſe he do as <hi>Saul</hi> did, make bold to do that which is unwarrantable; and ſo running before he be ſent, and doing that <hi>which God never ſpake any word about;</hi> the which he ſhall <hi>do well to take further knowledge of.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:123379:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Containing a defence of the judgement of ſuch as hold that Baptiſme hath continued Gods Ordinance in the Apoſtacie of Antichriſt, notwithſtanding the corruptions attending of it; in way of Anſwer to the Cavils and Exceptions of</hi> J. S. <hi>againſt the ſame.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore that <hi>J. S.</hi> could finiſh the matter in the former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and clear it as he pretended to do, he found ſome Tenents in his way, as oppoſite to that pretended truth (but indeed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) which he endeavoured to maintain; the which he ſetteth down thus: <hi>Firſt, ſuch as ſtand for a perſonall ſucceſſion:</hi> Again thus; <hi>A word or two to ſuch as hold ſucceſſion in the defection of Antichriſt:</hi> Again, <hi>Such as hold Baptiſme by perſonall ſucceſſion,</hi> as in <hi>pag.</hi> 39. may be ſeen.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer: Firſt, That ſure <hi>J. S.</hi> miſtaketh himſelf, being never able to make it appear, that any perſon, or perſons, do ſo hold. So I might let him alone to conteſt with his own fancie.</p>
               <p>But in as much as he may happily have met with ſome that hold the continuation of Baptiſme, as Gods Ordinance in that defection; not in way of <hi>ſucceſſion,</hi> that being no way proper to an Ordinance; returning home unto himſelf his phraſe of <hi>ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as darkening the truth: I ſhall apply my ſelf to take knowledge of his ſcope and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he ſaith, Such have <hi>received a ſufficient Anſwer that hold ſo, in what he had writ before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer: Indeed, if he might be his own Judge in his own cauſe, it might be ſo: It were much better that others ſhould have ſaid ſo, and praiſed him, then he thus his own work: But what was it that he had proved before in his conceit? <hi>That all the world are unbaptized,</hi> onely he, and thoſe of his way: Is he not a mighty Champion, thus to nullifie and make void the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:123379:21"/> of all Chriſtians in the world? It is more then Turks could ever do by all the force and power they had.</p>
               <p>He hath yet a word or two more to ſay to ſuch as hold contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (to his erroneous concluſion) that Baptiſme hath continued, and doth continue Gods Ordinance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And firſt, he begins by way of Querie, thus: <hi>If they mean by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, the outward form of worſhip, and Government Eccleſiaſticall, as he thinketh they do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is defection of ſo hard and doubtfull ſenſe with <hi>J. S.</hi> as he ſhould querie thus, and go by thinking: he may know that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection or defilement, pollution or corruption, are of one nature, and that there is a reall difference betwixt corruption, and the thing corrupted; between defilement, and the thing defiled; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Religion, and Gods Ordinances; and mens additions to, and detractions from the ſame: They mean that the Ordinances, and in particular, Baptiſme hath continued from the Apoſtles downward, thorow all the apoſtacie and defilements that have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Religion and it to this day; Juſt as Circumeiſion of old did continue Gods Ordinance in the apoſtacie and defilements of the ten Tribes under <hi>Jeroboam:</hi> and likewiſe in the time of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in <hi>Judah:</hi> This is their meaning, and what then? <hi>Then, ſaith he, all the power and authority that ever carried out any Adminiſtration or conſtituted Ordinance depends on the ſame:</hi> (Juſt as Circumciſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on the Calves in <hi>Jeroboams</hi> apoſtacie) <hi>And if ſo, ſaith he, then the Ordainer, and Ordinance ordained, are both of one nature:</hi> (Yea, they are both of one nature; God is the Author, he is ſpirituall; and Baptiſme, the thing ordained, ſo alſo.) <hi>If one be, ſaith he, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, the other is alſo Antichriſtian:</hi> Strong lines without proof. What if neither be Antichriſtian, neither the Authour nor Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, where is <hi>J. S.</hi> then? For truly his collective reaſon is as much, as if a perſon oppoſing Circumciſion, as none of Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, becauſe of the Idolatry of the Jews, ſhould have reaſoned thus: If the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> be <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and the <hi>Calves Idols,</hi> and no gods; and the Prieſts Prieſts to them that <hi>are no gods,</hi> then is Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion <note place="margin">2 Chro. 13. 9.</note> of the ſame nature alſo as are the Calves, &amp; Prieſts, and <hi>Jeroboams</hi> whole way of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi> And for proof, ſhould ſay as <hi>J. S.</hi> doth, that it was the power of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> way, or of his Calves that carried on the whole form of worſhip, and proceed: and the power, and Ordainer, and the Ordinance ordained, muſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:123379:22"/> needs be of one ſtamp; if one ſo, then ſo the other: Had not ſuch a way of arguing overthrown Circumciſion then, aſwell as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme now: Let <hi>J. S.</hi> be Judge himſelf, and let him tell me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would not have diſtinguiſhed in the caſe.</p>
               <p>Againe, I will propoſe another inſtance in the way of his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Thus the Author and thing ordained or made, muſt be of one and the ſame nature; if one be Antichriſtian, the other alſo, <hi>for ſo he hath proved, be ſaith.</hi> But the Authors, namely, thoſe that tranſlated the Scripture, were according to his opinion, Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and there be additions and detractions, as in ſome tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions there are: Now the thing made or tranſlated, muſt be of the ſame nature with the Tranſlators that were the Authors, and if it were added for proof, it was the power of their Antichriſtian ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that carried on the whole worke and proceed thereof; and ſo conclude as before, both are one and the ſame. If <hi>J. S.</hi> now would in this ſtand to his own ground, where would he be, he would be as far to ſeek for new Scriptures, as they are for <hi>Church; and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> that hold there neither is nor yet can be any in the World; or as he himſelf was not long ſince for Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>But truly it is much to be pittyed, to ſee ſuch ignorance in men profeſſing knowledge, that they cannot diſtinguiſh betwixt <hi>Gods</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 4. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>poſts and mens,</hi> when mens are ſet by Gods. That they cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between Gods Ordinances and mens inventions and adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; that they cannot put difference betwixt the <hi>Arke and Dagon, or his Temple,</hi> in which he being placed <hi>fell before the Arke:</hi> I would <note place="margin">1. Sam. 5. 4.</note> faine know of <hi>J. S.</hi> when Baptiſme, that was Chriſts, ſeaſed, and loſt its being, and Antichriſts Baptiſme came in the roome of it, ſure he cannot tell.</p>
               <p>But I muſt here tell <hi>J. S.</hi> that the power of Jeſus Chriſt ſupports and carries his Ordinances in the midſt of the deepeſt defections that Satan ever hath or could bring upon the ſame, wherein his glorious power doth appear; although <hi>J. S.</hi> would ſpoile him of it, by faining that he is overcome, &amp; his Church &amp; Ordinances de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Gods people of old remained his people; his Church, his Church; his Ordinances, his Ordinances; as particularly Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the midſt of the greateſt defilements that ever attended that diſpenſation. In like manner it is ſo now, under al the defilements of Antichriſt, in particular, Baptiſme, of which is our queſtion; as alſo the Church: our Lord Chriſt his power being no way leſſened for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:123379:22"/> the upholding of it, nor his faithfulneſſe failed for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, according to his promiſe; who hath ſaid, <hi>The gates</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it:</hi> It were good for <hi>J. S.</hi> to ſtudy well that place 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Where Antichriſt is foretold, ſitting in the Temple or Church of God;</hi> and if he would pleaſe but to take notice, that there is difference between Gods Temple, in which he ſitteth, and him ſitting there; as there was betwixt the Arke in the Temple of <hi>Dagon,</hi> in which the Arke was, he happily would change his thoughts, and be of another minde, and ſo come to have more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective thoughts of the power and faithfulneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, then now he ſeemeth to have. Truly I ſuppoſe theſe fooliſh infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of <hi>J. S.</hi> will appear to be but meer fantaſies, without any ground, tending only to deceive the ſimple; for any indifferent Reader will be able to diſtinguiſh betwixt Religion and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, betwixt Ordinances and the evills, (by way of addition or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction) that attends them; Circumciſion was of God, and it was the hand and power of God that carried it forth in thoſe evill times. The Idols, Calves, and <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Prieſts, and his whole way as they were of, and from another, ſo another hand and power carried them along. Even as in like manner Baptiſme and other like things being of God, are preſerved and carried by a hand and power of God; whereas that univerſall Church, generall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery and government, with thoſe other forms of Churches Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall, Dioceſan, and proportionall Miniſtery and Government, Ceremonies, with additions and detractions innumerable, as they are from another fountain, ſo they are carried in another chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, and by another power abetted and ſet on: namely, by the power of the man of ſin, the author and inventer of them. So far ſhall ſuffice in this.</p>
               <p>But ſaith <hi>J. S.</hi> praiſing of himſelf, <hi>He hath proved, that if one be Antichriſtian, the other is Antichriſtian:</hi> By what Scripture he hath proved it none can tell. And, ſaith he, <hi>To dream of any approved Church by the Word of God, under the defection, and yet a part of the ſame, is for a man to look for a man in the Moon; and to ſuppoſe a Church to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in ſuch matter as is deſtructive to it ſelf; and therein to hold a ſucceſſisn of truth is againſt the light of nature, and a keeping of the Pope upon the Throne of Chriſt whether he will or no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is not this high Divinity which <hi>I. S.</hi> belcheth out of his ſelf-ſick ſtomack againſt the people and truth of God: Is it not a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:123379:23"/> ſore and heavy charge? but it is well, it is but ſaid, and not proved. Now leaſt any, as ſimple as he that ſaid it, ſhould believe it becauſe it is ſaid, and that by a perſon venerable in their way, I ſhall take the pains to examine the reſpective charges as they are laid down. Firſt, ſaith he, <hi>To dream of an approved Church by the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sure he dreamed himſelf in what he fathered thus upon his oppoſites, who do not hold an approved Church in ſuch a ſenſe as <hi>J. S.</hi> ſeemeth to intend, that is, a pure and ſpotleſſe Church: But they hold according to the Scripture, a Church to be really true, and Gods, though corrupt and greatly defiled. I ſuppoſe he will not queſtion but that <hi>Judah,</hi> (not to ſpeak of <hi>Iſrael)</hi> was the Church of God in <hi>Manaſſes</hi> time, and in other times when Idolatry great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevailed, yet not approved as pure and ſpotleſſe, but reproved for corruption and defilement; yea, and <hi>viſited with the rods of men</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 89. 3 2.</note> becauſe of the ſame, that ſhe might be reformed, ſo as to be again approved of her head and husband, that all this time of her back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding did not renounce her. In ſhort, ſhe was approved to be, but not approved as pure in that her being. And ſurely ſo is the caſe of the Church where <hi>Antichriſt ſits as God,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 4. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo conſidered, let <hi>J. S.</hi> when he awaketh make the moſt he can of it.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of the dream is this, <hi>that this is a part of the ſame,</hi> I ſuppoſe he meaneth corrupt, as the whole is. To which I anſwer, though it be corrupt, yet it is no part of the corruption, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing difference, as before, betwixt a thing and the corruption that attends it; the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were a part of the Schiſme of <hi>Jeroboam, The ſeven thouſand were a part of the ten Tribes which went aſtray.</hi> In a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe <note place="margin">1 King. 19. 18.</note> ſenſe perſons may be of the Church of God, and members for their parts, and yet in a way of Idolatry, and in that way none <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 27. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with 1 Cor. 5. 1. 1 Cor. 25. 12.</note> of Gods, as may be further ſeen by the caſe of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> as alſo of the Prieſt that went aſtray, that went along with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in their Idolatry, ſure there is little in this part of the whole.</p>
               <p>But in the third place in his deep charge, he ſaith, this <hi>is to look for a man in the Moon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Juſt as <hi>J. S.</hi> did look for the Church and Baptiſme in the Scriptures: Indeed <hi>Eliah</hi> thought, as his complaint ſheweth, that he was left alone, but God told him otherwiſe: for ſure to <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 3, 4.</note> minde a Church, as retaining her being, though in a corrupt eſtate is no looking for a man in a Moon; though he, for want of other
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:123379:23"/> matter and better proofe, is pleaſed out of his <hi>ſick ſtomack</hi> to ſay ſo againſt the truth, and ſuch as ſtand for it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, ſaith he, <hi>It is to ſuppoſe a Church to conſiſt in ſuch matter as is deſtructive to it ſelf.</hi> Sure <hi>J. S.</hi> cannot make out this in any ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall way, it is but a part of his dream; to hold a Church to conſiſt of matter corrupt and degenerate, as was the <hi>Idolatrous Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> and as was the <hi>lukewarme Laodiceans,</hi> is not to hold amiſſe, is not to hold the matter deſtructive to the form or being. <hi>The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full City becomming ſometime a harlot:</hi> Indeed ſuch matter is againſt <note place="margin">Eſa. 1. 21.</note> the well being of the Church, but that is not our queſtion: the matter of the Church ought to be holy and pure, but it is often otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, he ſaith, to hold a continuedneſſe of the Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (though not of her well being) his term is here <hi>ſucceſſion of truth,</hi> but he meaneth ſure, the Churches being: <hi>It is againſt the light of nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A marvellous high aſcent and ſore charge, but it is but raſhly ſpoken, as one in a dream, that loveth no inferences: But however it is well it is not againſt the light of the holy Scriptures, <hi>J. S.</hi> hath left them, and is gone to the light of nature: but how doth the light of nature teach, that a Church and Ordinances, of which is our queſtion, cannot continue their being, if corrupt or greatly corrupted. Truly no more then in the caſe of <hi>Job,</hi> that he ſhould not, or could not be a man, becauſe corrupt, <hi>Job</hi> 2. 7. The folly and weakneſſe of this fifth part of the dream, I ſuppoſe any weak judgement will be able to ſee, and I will ſay no more. In the ſixth place to bring up the reare, he addeth a charge of a foule na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: That to hold a continuance of the Church and Ordinances under the apoſtacy of Antichriſt, <hi>Is a keeping of the Pope upon the throne of Chriſt whether he will or no:</hi> But how doth this appear, truly as all the reſt, becauſe he ſaies ſo. I would ask <hi>J. S.</hi> or any other, if the holding the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of the ten Tribes, to be <hi>Gods people,</hi> and their <hi>Circumciſion</hi> to be Gods Ordinances, did thus keep up that apoſtacy, and the Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> perforce, as in the place of God and his waies. Againe, doth <hi>J. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way, becauſe they hold the continuation of the ſame Scriptures, and which is more tranſlated by Antichriſtians in their ſenſe, and ſo ſucceſſively from <hi>Pope Jone:</hi> doth he or they in thus doing, keep the Pope upon the throne of Chriſt whether he will or no? It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:123379:24"/> him to ſee to it, and to renounce and caſt away thoſe <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Scriptures,</hi> as he hath done his Baptiſme, and ſo ſeek new Scriptures too; leſt not being true to his owne principles, hee ſhould become guilty of keeping the <hi>Pope upon the Throne of Chriſt whether he will or no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Experience, the School-miſtris of fooles, hath ſhewed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of this charge in the Reformed Churches, who have almoſt unthroned the <hi>Pope;</hi> of whom <hi>J. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way, as if they had ſome compaſſion, have buſied themſelves in making a little Terret &amp; Throne for him to ſit upon and inhabit in; namely, their <hi>Babel</hi> practiſe. And certainly their erroneous practiſe and way doth more help to keep the Pope upon the Throne of Chriſt, then any other thing that pretends oppoſition to it, as that courſe doth, of which a little more hereafter; and for the preſent I ſhall onely here aske <hi>J. S.</hi> whether he doe think the Pope doth ſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne of Chriſt yea or no; if he ſay yea, then ſure hee ſitteth in the Temple of God in the Church, for Chriſts Throne is there.</p>
               <p>He proceedeth after that great charge, thus: <hi>But to lay the chain of ſucceſſion of truth this way, namely through the Popedome of Rome, as all ſuch muſt doe that hold a perſonall ſucceſſion of a Church &amp; Ordinances to conſiſt in the ſame from the Apoſtles untill now; What will ſuch doe, and where will their ſucceſſion of truth lye when they come to the woman Pope, of whom the Papiſts themſelves are aſhamed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In anſwer I retort it thus, to lay the chain of ſucceſſion of truth this way; namely, through the Popedome, as all ſuch muſt doe that hold the writing or the letter of the Scriptures to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued from the Apoſtles untill now in a way of perſonall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in that defection; what will ſuch doe when they come to the woman Pope, of whom the Papiſts themſelves are aſhamed; truly <hi>J. S.</hi> hath cauſe to be aſhamed of his fooliſh reaſon, which if it were true, he would finde himſelfe to be at as great a fault as his oponent.</p>
               <p>But further, I ſay, ſuch as hold the continuation of the Church and Ordinances through Popiſh defection, or under the ſtate of the Popedome, will doe well enough with their tenent, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Pope <hi>Jone,</hi> who could never reach the Churches being, to cauſe it to ceaſe; nor yet Baptiſme, of which in ſpeciall is our queſtion; all the coined words of <hi>J. S.</hi> put upon the matter will
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:123379:24"/> not doe it; <hi>as his chain of ſucceſſion of truth,</hi> in ſtead of continuation of Baptiſme; again, <hi>hold a perſonall ſucceſſion;</hi> again, <hi>where will their ſucceſſion of truth lye:</hi> All theſe being returned home to <hi>J. S.</hi> their maſter, he will ſee, or at leaſtwiſe any indifferent perſon will be able to ſee, that Pope <hi>Jone</hi> will help nothing in the caſe, to hinder the continuance of the Churches being, nor yet of the being of Baptiſme, with which Pope <hi>Jone</hi> medled not, nor was any way concerned: this matter at the moſt is but a relique of the dram before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I. S.</hi> further tells us, <hi>that when he ſpeakes of perſonall ſucceſſion of truth, as in reference to Church and Church Ordinances, he looks upon this in the power and authority tbat beares the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now <hi>J. S.</hi> ſeemeth ſomething to awaken out of his dreame and to ſpeak ſenſe, what ever ſenſe he have in it <hi>(his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſucceſſion of truth ſet aſide)</hi> when <hi>he ſpeaketh of the Church and Ordinances their continuance, he looketh upon this in the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that beares the ſame.</hi> Now ſurely, the power and authority that beares the Church and Church Ordinance up, is the power of him that <hi>beareth up all things by his mighty power, Jeſus Chriſt our</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord,</hi> againſt the <hi>gates of hell,</hi> that preſerves his Church, as hee did his Arke, when <hi>Dagon fell in his owne Temple.</hi> Is it not a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull <note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note> thing, that he ſhould conceit that Antichriſt ſhould by any power of his, ſupport Chriſts Church and the Ordinances thereof, that with all his might and force indeavoureth their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and ruine? but in vaine, for Chriſt is ſtronger, that with his mighty power ſupports them.</p>
               <p>But <hi>J. S.</hi> looking awry, cannot ſee any other bearing up the Church and Ordinances, then by Antichriſt and the Pope, that are trampling it down what they can, fitting there as God; for by no meanes will he be brought to diſtinguiſh and put difference betwixt Gods Temple, and the Man of ſinne ſitting in it, but like <hi>Nicodemus</hi> he will ſay, <hi>How can it be,</hi> Joh. 3.</p>
               <p>For ſaith he, <hi>To hold a Church to be true</hi> (in regard of being, you muſt mind, and not of purity) <hi>and the Ordinances their adminiſtred the true Ordinances of God, and to leave this, and to ſet up a way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip apart from it, and to deny communion with it; is in his darke underſtanding a meere Schiſme and the overthrow of all Order in Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I am both glad and ſorry: Glad, that <hi>J. S.</hi> is no Apoſtle,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:123379:25"/> ſo as we are not bound to beleeve his bare word, unleſſe we will: Sorry I am, that he hath ſo dark a judgement and underſtanding, as in this he doth diſcover: For firſt, I ſay, a Church may be true, and the Ordinances true, that is Gods; and yet both corrupt, ſo as they cannot be partaken with all without ſin. In ſuch a caſe there is to be a with-drawing from them, in regard of particular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; in as much as we are to <hi>keep our ſelves pure,</hi> not <hi>doing evill for good ends:</hi> Yea, a Church in regard of memberſhip may be left, and that without the ſaid Churches conſent, as plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the example of the Apoſtles and others that left the <hi>Church of Iſrael</hi> of old, and that while it was a Church: And God himſelfe calleth his people out of <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 18. 4. though the Church and Ordinances have a being there; in as much as there can be no remaining there, but there will be a partaking in ſinne. So as leaving particular communion, and perſonall relation of memberſhip, I conceive is very neceſſary, and according to God, after the manner of all the Reformed Churches that have <hi>come out of Babylon,</hi> &amp; renounced communion with her in the things of God, becauſe of the evills attending of them, <hi>leſt they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed.</hi> As on the other ſide, they have drawn nigh to God in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his wayes and worſhip; as thoſe did that left <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the time of their Apoſtacie, and came to the Lord and his pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in <hi>Judah.</hi> But thus to doe, namely, to leave a Church and Ordinances greatly polluted and defiled, and to worſhip God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether purely, apart from that corrupted eſtate, with-holding fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, is in his dark judgement a meer Schiſme; (alas poor dark judgement) ſuch a Schiſme as he hath oft made and thoſe of his way are full of in their own ſenſe. The holy Apoſtles and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Jewes were Schiſmaticks in his account; and all the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches and Chriſtians that have forſaken <hi>Babylon</hi> and are come out of her, are all Schiſmaticks in his dark judgement: But no marvell he ſo accounteth of theſe latter, ſeeing by his reckoning they are not baptized Chriſtians. Truly he, and thoſe of his way, by light and cleare judgements will be diſcerned to be even ſuch themſelves, for doing as they doe.</p>
               <p>Now to that latter part of this charge, <hi>That it is the overthrow of all order in Religion:</hi> I aske him which way it appeareth ſo to be; ſure he cannot tell; for if it be well minded, it will be found to be a ſpeciall meanes of the preſerving of religion decayed, and a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:123379:25"/> repayring of it, and of reducing it to the firſt purity, and an utter putting away all ruſt and defilement; and therefore the Apoſtle giveth in charge, having forewarned of the great defection of Antichriſt, not to begin a new; but to <hi>keep the</hi> (old) <hi>Ordinances, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Theſ. 2. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>to the purity they were delivered to us. J. S.</hi> his courſe, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is guilty of the overthrow of all order in Religion, not onely what is of God, remaining, and afoot in the world; but even of that alſo which is held forth in the Word: in erecting a new Church, and diſpenſing new Ordinances, without a new Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which never any did before.</p>
               <p>After this, he tells us <hi>of his learning Chriſt,</hi> which ſure is very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, in regard of order, as his way and courſe doth ſhew: So far, faith he, <hi>as I have learned Chriſt, men are to ſtand in their places, and uſe all means to reclaim and reform</hi> (corrupt Churches he meaneth) <hi>by the word of truth.</hi> Very good; But what if they will not reform, and all means which we can uſe availeth not? This being done, ſaith he, <hi>ſo as of neceſſity I muſt leave off communion with them.</hi> So as it ſeemeth communion may be left with a Church that is Gods, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of evill, and obſtinacie in the ſame. Then in ſuch a caſe he <hi>thinketh</hi> (for he onely giveth us his thoughts without Scripture) <hi>he muſt diſclaim them, and ſeparate from them.</hi> To which I ſay, it is but upon the condition of their non-repentance, which challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſometime of waiting: but that ſuch a Church he ought to diſclaim, and ſeparate from, he holdeth. Firſt, I would know, whether he may do this while it remaineth a Church of Chriſt? If he ſay yea; then I ask him, What is become of that which <hi>in his dark judgement was a meer Schiſme?</hi> But if he ſay nay, not till the Church ceaſes to be: Truly, that will be a very hard matter for him to determine, eſpecially to hit upon the very hour of ſuch a Churches death, from which time he is freed from her relation without Schiſme. But yet further, he holdeth, as before; <hi>He muſt ſtand in his place, and uſe all means to reform, and reclaim ſuch a Church by the word of God.</hi> Indeed, I ſay, that is a good medicine, and wholeſome plaiſter to heal ſuch a diſeaſe and maladie: I would fain know whether he be not to wait to ſee the iſſue; and whether he be not to exerciſe long patience after the example of Almighty God, <hi>that ſent his Prophets to his Church, riſing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 25. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>early, and ſending them;</hi> and notwithſtanding their wickedneſſe, and abuſe of his long patience, did not diſclaim them, or his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:123379:26"/> unto them, till ſuch time as they rejected the Son himſelf, and ſo <hi>were broken off through unbeleef.</hi> But further, if this his good me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine of admonition, reproof, and uſe of all good means in his <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 20.</note> place, ſhall not avail; but in ſtead of curing, the Church ſhall be killed; that were a ſad matter indeed. But however, the Phyſician ſhall not loſe his reward, though the patient die. But oh! to know whether ſhe be dead in all the parts of her, every member, is a hard matter to know: happily ſhe may have life in her inward parts; to bury her, before quite dead, were an ill buſineſſe. Sure out of ſo great a labyrinth as <hi>J. S.</hi> his thoughts neceſſarily led into this way, he will no way know which way to get forth, unleſſe he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſhall ingeniouſly confeſſe the darkneſſe of his judgement to have deceived him, and ſo acknowledge that a Church may be left in regard of communion, and memberſhip, by reaſon of great corruption and defilement, and that though it retain the being of a Church of Chriſt, and that without any Schiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. S.</hi> goeth over this matter again, on the negative, by a back blow of the left hand, ſaying, <hi>And not to leave a true Church, and true Ordinances,</hi> (though never ſo corrupt and defiled, and therein obſtinate and impenitent) <hi>and go apart to ſet up another Church, and Ordinance,</hi> (that is, ſerving God together, in the freedom and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Ordinances, as the reformed Churches do) <hi>apart from it, and in oppoſition to it: This is as far from the Rule of the Goſpel, as for a man to baptize himſelf; neither of which he approveth of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. J. S.</hi> Laying down the matter to his own advantage, may happily make it ſeem ſomething; but if it be well ſifted, and ſcanned, it will be found juſt nothing. The leaving a Church in defection, and gathering or going to a Church gathered in free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and purity, is the matter in queſtion: The refraining Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances corrupt, ſo as they cannot be partaken withall without ſin, we being required to keep our ſelves pure, for the Saints to ſerve God together in the freedom of his Ordinances purely: Sure he will not count this againſt the rule of the Goſpel; if he do, it is not for want of ignorance: Where is the pinch in this caſe? It is ſurely in this, <hi>of erecting another Church.</hi> To which I ſay, it is but another in number, by multiplication, not in nature; ſure he doth not queſtion that neither, they practiſe ſuch, multiplying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their way. What then muſt it be? That it is <hi>in oppoſition to the other:</hi> To which, I ſay, it is but in oppoſition to the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:123379:26"/> and defilements of the other; ſo as here is a pure Church, and Ordinances in their Adminiſtrations, in oppoſition to a Church and Ordinances adminiſtred corruptly. So far is this from an evill, as ſure it is a high vertue in Churches and particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; ſo, as to ſay no more, having before treated of this matter. Betwixt thus doing in this caſe, and a mans baptizing himſelf, <hi>J. S.</hi> may ſee a wide difference, if prejudice doth not let him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. S.</hi> hath yet a word more: <hi>Becauſe ſome hold it an errour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out example or warrant from the Word, for a man to baptize himſelfe or others, being himſelf unbaptized: whereby, ſaith he, they think to ſhut up the Ordinance in ſuch a ſtrait, as none can come by it, but through the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Popedome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A ſtrait it is indeed, as great as <hi>Saul</hi> was in, when <hi>he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 13. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>fooliſhly to ſacrifice;</hi> and this he will finde every day more and more, there being not a few as rationall as himſelf late of his way, that do ſee this; and rather then acknowledge their errour and return, proceed to a further and greater errour: namely, to hold no Church of God, nor Ordinance of Chriſt, exiſting in the world, nor none to be had, nor injoyed, till <hi>Chriſt perſonally</hi> again appear, or ſend ſuch to reſtore them, as by <hi>miracles</hi> can evince their miſſion. Such an opinion he is not unacquainted with: I wiſh him to conſider further of it, and ſee if it be not rationall from his ground, though very irrationall and unreaſonable for Chriſtian men to beleeve, without ground of Scripture, againſt ſo many clear evidences of holy Writ, and faithfull promiſes of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 18. &amp; 28. 20. <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 39. <hi>Heh.</hi> 12. 28, 29. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 55. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the opening of this cloud,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that ſeems ſo to darken the skie, let the Reader conſider who baptized</hi> John (I ſay let them rather conſider <hi>Johns</hi> particular &amp; ſpeciall commiſſion) before he baptized others; <hi>and if no man did, then, whether he did not baptize others, himſelf being unbaptized: and if he was baptized, whether it was not by an unbaptized perſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Inſtance referreth it ſelf to the beginning of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme at the firſt, and ſo it is brought, in way of parallel, to prove the new beginning of Baptiſme, that former being loſt and cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of the world.</p>
               <p>Now, if this matter be minded, <hi>John</hi> was (according to what was foretold) <hi>ſent of God to prepare the way of Chriſt,</hi> and had ſpeciall <note place="margin">John 1. 6.</note>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:123379:27"/> warrant in particular wiſe to Baptize: as it is written: <hi>There was a man ſent of God, his name was</hi> John. So as if this prove any thing, it muſt be upon the ſame ground; that is, having the ſame War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and Commiſſion in particular, as <hi>John</hi> had: for as <hi>Iohns</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample would not ſerve any, in thoſe times, to go without Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or Baptize without command, being unbaptized themſelves; <hi>Cornelius</hi> muſt have <hi>Peter; Paul, Ananias; and our Lord himſelf, for righteouſneſſe ſake, muſt go to</hi> John: Even ſo in like kinde, it will not ſerve any now to recover and raiſe (as they pretend) the Ordinance of Baptiſme loſt and fallen out of the world, without ſpeciall warrant, as he had.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt is ſtill catched at for help, in this helpleſſe cauſe, I ſhall adde a word or two: Firſt, The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly way of raiſing Baptiſme, <hi>I. S.</hi> holdeth to be by the Churches power and appointment, and this way they proceed. But <hi>Iohns</hi> Commiſſion, it was not from the Church, but it was immediatly from God that ſent him to prepare the way of his Son.</p>
               <p>Secondly, concerning <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Scripture teſtifieth; That he was <hi>a Prophet, and more then a Prophet:</hi> But how, or what, or whether or <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 9.</note> no concerning his particular Baptiſme, it is altogether ſilent. It is not for men to be over wiſe, or meddle above what is written; but let the body of <hi>Moſes</hi> alone.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, I will put it upon this Iſſue; In the judgement of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different men, whether they think it will follow, that becauſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> were the firſt beginners and actors in <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> by vertue of ſpeciall Commiſſion to them perſonally; that therefore it was lawfull of old, in caſe of <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> for any of the heathen to have alſo <hi>circumciſed</hi> themſelves and families: or in the caſe of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> for others at that time, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his example, to have baptized alſo as he did, without any Commiſſion at all; for if in thoſe times it was not lawfull for them ſo to do, but of neceſſity they muſt go, as our Lord did, to the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> then in as much as length of time, can give no warrant, to a thing not warrantable at the firſt; I conceive it will be given, and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that Inſtance is invalide, and of no force to warrant a perſon to baptize himſelf, or others, being himſelf unbaptized.</p>
               <p>Which he in the caſe of Baptiſme, ſaith, <hi>was written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and teacheth us what to do upon the like occaſion.</hi> To which I ſay, ſuppoſing the occaſion, he here ſpeaketh of, is not that of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:123379:27"/> that hath no law; but leaveth men at liberty to do the beſt they can: which is the laſt refuge of <hi>I. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way: There is, I ſay, no ſuch occaſion as in the caſe of <hi>Iohn,</hi> there being <hi>no Scripture to be fulfilled by ſending a meſſenger before to prepare Chriſts</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 3. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>way.</hi> There is no ſuch occaſion, for that there is no new Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, nor any new Ordinances to be ſet on foot. Again, there is no ſuch occaſion, for that there is baptized perſons in the world to repair unto; that as Chriſt our Lord went to <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſo we might go to them.</p>
               <p>Beſides, what is not written, cannot be for our learning. Now it is not written, when, or where, or by whom, or whether at all <hi>Iohn</hi> was baptized, ſo as none of any ſuch things can be for our learning, unleſſe we will go beyond our Leſſon: But this is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that he was ſent of God, and had ſpeciall Commiſſion to do what he did; that we might learn, not to run before we be ſent, but to be obedient in going when we are bidden, and doing as we are commanded, as he did.</p>
               <p>Further <hi>I. S.</hi> ſaith, <hi>for the continuance of the Church from Chriſts words: The gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi> Here by the way, I take notice, that he hath laid aſide his <hi>ſucceſſion, and perſonall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and ſpeaks now plain Engliſh; namely, the continuation of the Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 18.</p>
               <p>Now what ſaith he to this? <hi>He confeſſeth the ſame:</hi> But in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he overthroweth his new way and courſe; for if the Church continue, and hath continued, what need is there of new begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and baptizing by perſons unbaptized: ſurely none at all. And therefore he maketh his acknowledgement with a <hi>proviſo;</hi> that is, by a diſtinction that indeed is either a non-ſenſe, or elſe a flat deniall. The diſtinction is thus: That <hi>this Church is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, in her inſtituted State, as it lieth in the Scriptures; in the rules of the foundation.</hi> (See what expreſſions are here; Inſtituted State, Rules of foundation, Lying in the Scripture; as much, and no more then this, according to the pattern ſet forth in the Word) <hi>Or otherwiſe in the ſecond place, in her Conſtitation, or conſtituted form, in her viſible Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> As much as if he had ſaid, in her outward being. Now of the pattern is not our queſtion; for as the pattern of the Temple was one thing, and the Temple built, or to be built, was another thing; ſo it is here. But ſee what <hi>J. S.</hi> ſaith, having made ſuch a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as before, to darken the truth: Thus he ſaith, <hi>Againſt the</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:123379:28"/> 
                  <hi>firſt hell gates never prevailed.</hi> This pattern ſtanding ſure in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as of old the pattern of the Temple might remaine, when the Temple was deſtroyed. <hi>But againſt the Church it ſelf,</hi> which is the ſecond part of his diſtinction, <hi>it hath prevailed.</hi> So the ſumme is as much, as if he had ſaid, hell gates never prevailed againſt the Scriptures; but againſt the Church, built according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, it hath. Now let any man excuſe the irrationalneſſe of <hi>I. S.</hi> if he can; thus to grant in ſhew, and deny in ſubſtance and truth, with one breath, the continuation of the Church, according to the Word and ptomiſe of Chriſt, made to the Church, and not to the Scriptures. <hi>And I ſay unto thee, thou art</hi> Peter; <hi>and upon this rocke</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 18.</note> (to wit himſeif) <hi>I will build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it to deſtroy it.</hi> For why, it was built on a ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not to be moved for ever.</p>
               <p>Now this Church, the continuation whereof he granted before, having deceived himſelf and his Reader, by a groundleſſe diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he denieth the continuation now, and ſaith, <hi>Hell gates hath prevailed often againſt it.</hi> But whence is it that he is thus contrary, and I and no? Saith he, <hi>For the Church hath been often in her outward order ſcattered through perſecution and the like.</hi> Sure this is a very weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſon, thus to over power a man; what if the Church hath bin ſcattered through perſecution, muſt it then follow, a deſtroying by hell gates: though the Church <hi>hath been greatly ſcattered through perſecution,</hi> yet ſhe continued her being, and was ſo far from being by hell gates prevailed againſt, as that they overcame by ſuffering <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> the gates of hell, and were <hi>more then conquerers.</hi> The blood of the Martyrs being the ſeed of the Church, and the Church the more oppreſſed, the more growing and increaſing. <hi>J. S.</hi> ſaith, <hi>in this ſenſe of being ſcattered, ſhe is ſaid to be overcome.</hi> To which I ſay, that this is not the ſenſe of <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 18. nay, it is againſt the ſenſe of the Scripture, that by afflictions the Church ſhould be overcome, when as in all afflictions the Church hath <hi>been more then conquerers through Chriſt that loved her. I. S.</hi> citeth two or three places, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 1. For that in <hi>Daniel,</hi> it is utterly againſt his ſenſe, for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Kingdome of Chriſt his Church, it ſaith, it ſhall not be deſtroyed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. 27. As for that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. it plainly declareth the prevailing of the Church, and not her being overcome or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that they <hi>overcame by the blood of the Lambe,</hi> and <hi>that the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon was caſt out.</hi> It indeed ſpeaketh of the <hi>womans fleeing into the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 12.</note>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:123379:28"/> 
                  <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> but there ſhe was preſerved and not deſtroyed, the earth helping the woman againſt the rage of the Dragon. Sure there can no ſenſe hence be gathered, of hell gates prevailing to deſtroy her. Laſtly, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 1. It ſpeaketh of <hi>Sauls</hi> making havock of the Church, and perſecuting of it, but this tended greatly to the increaſe of it, and not to the deſtroying of it. Certainly <hi>I. S.</hi> will not think, much leſſe ſay, hell gates at this time prevailed againſt the Church, indeed it never did, for that was alwaies true which was ſaid of the Church of old, <hi>Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth, may</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 129. 1. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael ſay, but they have not prevailed againſt me, the righteous Lord hath cut the cords of the wicked in ſunder.</hi> I ſuppoſe <hi>I. S.</hi> hath but ſmall judgement, and leſſe aim, to bring ſuch Scriptures as theſe to prove that hell gates have prevailed againſt the Church in any Scripture ſenſe. It were far better for him to hold the continuation of the Church according to the ſure Word and faithfull promiſe of Chriſt, and if he would not acknowledge her continuance under the apoſtacy and defection aforeſaid, then to indeavour to find her continuance ſome where elſe. But in regard this would overthrow his new unbaptized Church, and proceed that way, he rather chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to aſperſe Chriſt of unfaithfulneſſe in his promiſe, then by acknowledgement to give him the glory of it.</p>
               <p>In regard of the former matter <hi>J. S.</hi> ſeemeth to have had an eye to a collaterall reaſon, which he ſetteth down thus: <hi>Where was their Church before it came out of the defection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, let it be obſerved how he ſhaketh hands with the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> that uſe to ſay in like manner, <hi>Where were the reformed Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Luther?</p>
               <p>But in further anſwer to this demand, I ſay, it was in regard of the matter of it in <hi>Babylon,</hi> as the ſeven thouſand were in the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy of <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> out of which apoſtacy of <hi>Babylon, God called them forth, Rev.</hi> 18. 4. And ſo, by the efficacy of that heavenly voice, they being drawn forth, they ſerved God in the purity of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, (a part,) as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that left <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and his Idol-worſhip <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1. 9.</note> at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and ſerved God at <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> Theſe turned from thoſe Idoll waies in <hi>Babylon, To the pure ſervice of God in Sion, and ſo kept according to the injunction the Ordinances, as they were delivered to them,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 15.</p>
               <p>This queſtion is of the nature of what we have treated on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, about leaving a corrupt Church for obſtinacy in evill; and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:123379:29"/> therefore I ſhall not further trouble my ſelf nor the Reader about it, being aſſured, it cannot reach ſo high, as make good any ſenſe of the deſtroying of the Church by perſecution, to which it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded here.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only here minde the Reader, that our queſtion is not of one particular Church, but of the ſtate of the Church remaining in one place or other with few or many, in freedome and purity, or in bondage and corruption, according eo various conditions and changes that attends her in the world, wherein ſhe is in all of thoſe conditions preſerved by <hi>Almighty God. I. S.</hi> addeth in his further proceed, ſaying, <hi>That which once was in ſuch a way of being, and ceaſes for a time, and then comes to the ſame eſtate againe, is and may truly be ſaid ever to continue, as</hi> Mat. 22. 31. <hi>with</hi> Luk. 20. 38. <hi>In which ſenſe the Church may be ſaid ever to continue, for though ſhe be caſt down at one time, yet god will raiſe her againe at another, ſo as ſhe ſhall never be prevailed againſt, ſo as to be utterly deſtryed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is plaine nontſenſe to me, firſt granting, then deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo the whole amounting to juſt nothing but a meer conceit.</p>
               <p>Here is the Church in a way of being, here is the Church ſeaſing to be for a time; here is the Church comming to live &amp; have being again; here is the Church that ceaſed to be for a time affirmed; (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly) to have ever a being, (juſt as the Temple had when it was deſtroyed,) here is the Church caſt downe, (that is, without being, for ſo he muſt mean, elſe he deceiveth,) here is the Church ſaid to be raiſed up by God againe, and her being reſtored to her; here is concluded the Church was never prevailed againſt, ſo as to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed. Truly, truth is ſtrong and prevaileth. <hi>I. S.</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not as of himſelf, but as overcome by the truth, which he fought to darken and turn aſide, but at laſt is forced to confeſſe it, as they were that had hand in crucifying Chriſt, that ſaid, <hi>Truly this was the Son of God,</hi> when they had before crucified him. So <note place="margin">Mat. 27. 54.</note> he in like manner is in the end forced after all, to confeſſe that the <hi>Church was never prevailed againſt, ſo as to be utterly deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I ſhall here obſerve how that what he before ſaid might be made a rationall matter, if it were rightly applyed, as thus; That which was once in ſuch a way of being, (that is to ſay, pure and undefiled, and for a time ceaſes ſo to be,) (that is, becomes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and defiled, like the <hi>faithfull City that became an harlot.)</hi> And <note place="margin">Eſ. 1. 21.</note>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:123379:29"/> then comes the ſame eſtate againe, (that is, to her former purity and holineſſe,) is, and may truly be ſaid, ever to have a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. In this ſenſe I would joine with <hi>J. S.</hi> touching the Churches continuation, for though ſhe be corrupted at one time, yet God will reſtore her to purity at another; yea, <hi>If by affliction ſhe be diminiſhed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 107. 39. Pſ. 105. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>and made low at one time, yet at another time God increaſeth her like a flock of ſheep.</hi> In either of which ſenſes ſhe hath never been prevailed againſt, ſo as to be deſtroyed: but this genuine ſenſe <hi>J. S.</hi> may not admit of, for that it will not ſtand with his way and practice, and therefore by multiplicity of expreſſions he would produce ſome thing: namely, <hi>That the Church may ſome time live, and have a being, and at another time die and loſe her being, and yet ſhe ſhall never ceaſe to be.</hi> That is, be prevailed againſt to be deſtroyed: and this he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to prove by alluding to a place or two of holy Scripture, before quoted, for confirmation of his conceit.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, thoſe Scriptures indeed do ſeem to illuſtrate his ſenſe, and what he intendeth; namely, that the Church may be ſaid ever to continue, though at ſome time ſhe ceaſed to be. But how ſenſeleſſe a thing it is thus to conceit, will appeare if we minde the matter a little. It is the reſurection of the dead which is the caſe: now as men die, and are not, and yet ſhall live again, and be; ſo the Church in like manner. But may ſuch and ſuch men be ſaid to have ever a continuance in the World, (which is our queſtion,) and not to have been deſtroyed by death, becauſe they ſhall riſe againe? Nay, doth not this prove plainly, that death had <hi>dominion</hi> over them, and that they were thereby deſtroyed? for otherwiſe, how ſhould there be place for their riſing again. And indeed the reſtoring of the Church to her being doth neceſſarily imply the loſſe of her being; otherwiſe there would be no place for reſtoring. If all men had been deſtroyed at the <hi>deluge of Noah,</hi> a new creation had been neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Happily he may think their is ſomething in that, <hi>that God is not the God of the dead, but of the living, in as much as all live to him.</hi> Indeed this may prove the ſoules immortality and living with God. But what ſenſe it hath in regard of the Church, is beyond my thoughts; for certainly, if it hath reference to the Church, it will enforce the being and continuace of the Church of the Jewes and the Patriarchall Churches which ceaſed long agoe: To imagine their continuance, what can be more vaine?</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:123379:30"/>
               <p>But further, if becauſe all live to God, therefore the Church alwayes hath a being, where is place left for her death and ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Truly this is a matter too far fetcht, to prove any thing in this matter that may ſtand him in any ſtead, for if any thing be gathered from it, it muſt be that; as <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets dyed and left the world; ſo the Church of Chriſt dyed alſo and was deſtroyed out of the world. But if he ſhall ſay, <hi>Abraham</hi> and the reſt lived notwithſtanding: The anſwer is, they lived indeed another way, not in regard of their mortall bodies, but in regard of their immortall ſoules. Their outward viſible bodies were deſtroyed and in the duſt; ſo the outward viſible Church is deſtroyed, and ceaſes to be; but the inwardneſſe of it (the life and ſoule, to wit, Jeſus Chriſt) is in heaven with God, what this maketh to the matter in hand I leave the Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this way, ſaith</hi> J. S. <hi>I ſuppoſe Chriſt may have and enjoy as good a wife ever as any can be preſerved for him under the defection of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This way is a meere ſuppoſition, without reaſon and againſt ſenſe: That Chriſt ſhould have ſometime a wife, and ſometime none, and then one againe; and yet he ſhould have ever one preſerved. It were good to lay aſide ſuch ſenſeleſſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and to beleeve the Scriptures, that <hi>tell us that the man of ſinne ſometime ſitteth in the Temple of God;</hi> and that Gods Temple <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 4.</note> remaineth; <hi>and hell gates ſhall not prevaile againſt it.</hi> Though the Church (Chriſts wife) may goe aſtray and be corrupted, yet he <note place="margin">Matth. 16. 18</note> that is her husband will not forſake, but will reform her and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine her, and put new garments on her; ſure he hath read what God ſaid of old to his Spouſe, <hi>Thou haſt played the harlot with many</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 3. 10. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>lovers, yet return to me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> I am thy husband and thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. But happily if he had then lived, hee would have ſuppoſed <note place="margin">Eſa. 54 5.</note> that Chriſt might have had, or have made to himſelfe a new (as he in this caſe endeavoureth to doe for him) as good a wife as that that was, ſo corrupt and defiled. The truth is, there is more rich grace and free mercy in Jeſus Chriſt then to take advantage and to refuſe, and put away, for he is <hi>the Lord that changeth not, and therfore his Church is not deſtroyed,</hi> no, notwithſtanding the evils ſhe <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 6.</note> falleth into, <hi>for he hateth putting away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were more ſutable for <hi>J. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way, to profeſſe <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 16.</note> the doctrine of workes, which is ſutable to their other opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:123379:30"/> then the doctrine of free grace, unleſſe they would be more true to their principles, as in this particular; more eſpecially, wherein they hold corruption diſſolveth the marriage bond, and maketh the relation to ceaſe, and cauſeth the <hi>everlaſting Lord to change, and his Covenant to faile for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 77. 8.</p>
               <p>The following complaint and ſtory, by which it is illuſtrated, I have ſpoken unto it before; in which matter of guilt, if hee and thoſe of his way ſhould take water and waſh their hands, they would notwithſtanding be no leſſe guilty then <hi>Pilate</hi> was of Jeſus blood.</p>
               <p>But after this, he telleth of his feares, and that is, <hi>that men put more in Baptiſme then doth of right belong to it, that doe preferre it before the Church and all other Ordinances beſides.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is not <hi>J. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way ſick of this diſeaſe, and that as dangerouſly as thoſe he is in ſuch feare of? how otherwiſe ſhould it be that they ſhould be ſo often baptized, over and over, and over againe, and make a Church, that they may make Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? I leave the Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>2. How doth this appeare which he ſo feareth in others, <hi>that they preferre it before the Cburch and all Ordinances beſide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is onely to the qualification of the matter externally, that it might be ſutable to the reſt of the building, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 26. But yet this charge is not altogether true, for they doe not preferre Baptiſme before the Word and the publiſhing of it, by which faith comes: Nay they doe not preferre it above, or before the Church; the Church being <hi>the pillar and ground of truth;</hi> that is, of the truth <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 15.</note> of Ordinances and divine worſhip, and ſo of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed of it in a right way, which Church the matter of it at the preparing of it by <hi>John</hi> was firſt baptized, and after laid together in the building. So of this matter thus, by <hi>Johns</hi> preaching prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and by his waſhing in the ſecond place fitted, was in after time gathered <hi>and laid into a holy building to the Lord,</hi> which Church way begun, and ſetled in the world, augmented and encreaſed: thoſe waſhed waſhing others, according to Chriſts appointment; never any unwaſhed perſon being added or laid into the building ſince the Church begun, it being neceſſary that the matter of the Temple be outwardly fitted, that it may ſute with the reſt of the building being laid thereon. So as <hi>J. S.</hi> may be ſatisfied that his feares in the firſt place are cauſeleſſe, the Church being on foot
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:123379:31"/> according to God, Baptiſme in adminiſtration followeth: But in further declaring the reaſon of his feares, he ſaith:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For they can erect a Church, take in and caſt out members, elect and ordaine officers, adminiſter the Supper, and all anew without looking after ſucceſſion any further then the Scriptures. But as for Baptiſme they muſt have that ſucceſſively from the Apoſtles, though it come through the hands of Pope</hi> Jone: <hi>what the reaſon of this is that men can doe all from the Word</hi> but onely Baptiſme, and that muſt come by man, even by the man of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To balance the thoughts of <hi>J. S.</hi> I will preſent a caſe to his conſideration, ſuppoſing he had lived in the Apoſtacie of the ten Tribes (yea of <hi>Judahs</hi> Apoſtacie) and returning to the Lord and his pure ſervice, as thoſe of the ten Tribes that went from <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Judah,</hi> had other Prieſts and Miniſters of the Law and ſervice of God, and a pure way of ſerving of God, onely that of circumciſion, they would continue that (though according to his conceit in the caſe of Baptiſme) it came from the two Calves. What would he have ſaid or thought of it in this caſe I would faine know? If they did well, it is good for us to imitate them in a like caſe.</p>
               <p>2. I ſay, as before more fully, I have ſhewed that this Church and Ordinances are but new in regard of purity, the other being corrupt; ſo all this he calleth new, is not like their new raiſing of the Church and Ordinances, as if thoſe before had loſt their being, and were not at all. In this their caſe which he ſo excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth againſt, there is expreſſe warrant, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>keep the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as they were delivered unto you;</hi> that is, purely.</p>
               <p>3. Baptized perſons, in the caſe of their returne from idoll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes and Apoſtacie, to the pure ſervice of God, are to look after Baptiſme no otherwiſe then circumciſed Jewes did in the like caſe when they returned unto the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 9. They were not to circumciſe themſelves, or be circumciſed again; yet the Heather comming along with them, they muſt be circumciſed. In like manner, Gods people comming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> according to the call of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 4. are not required to be again baptized, though the Jewes and other Heathen that imbrace the faith of Chriſt, are required to doe it, which I would wiſh <hi>I. S.</hi> and thoſe of his way to conſider of.</p>
               <p>4. For the continuation of the Church and Baptiſme, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:123379:31"/> qualification of the matter, the Scriptures fully give witneſſe unto (as before is ſhewed) ſo as is no need of beginning them a new in any ſenſe (unleſſe of purity) but other Ordinances are by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence laid by and out of uſe, ſomething in the room of them: and ſo are by the Church to be reſtored to their places, when the Church is purged and made pure.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, for this of Baptiſme, <hi>comming through the hands of Pope</hi> Jone, <hi>and from the man of ſin:</hi> It is a falſe and ſcandalous reproach; it cometh no more through <hi>the hands of Pope</hi> Jone, <hi>and the man of ſin,</hi> then the holy Scriptures did, or then Circumciſion did, through the hands of the two Galves of old. <hi>J. S.</hi> may be aſhamed ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch Gods holy Ordinance, by his good pleaſure preſerved to this day, I would wiſh him to call to mind his complaint &amp; ſtory before.</p>
               <p>And now in regard he is up with Pope <hi>Ione</hi> again, to diſgrace the truth, and thoſe that ſtand for it; whereby to make perſons afraid, and do they know not what; which after, they undo again, and ſo <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 18.</note> make themſelves every way <hi>treſpaſſers by deſtroying what they before built.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will note ſome particulars, wherein thoſe of his way ſhake hands with Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> and the man of ſin, and leave the Reader to judge who may be moſt juſtly taxed for affinity with Pope <hi>Jone,</hi> the reformed or ſeparated Churches, or thoſe of the new way of Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Firſt, thoſe of that way of Baptiſme hold generall or univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall redemption with the man of ſin and Pope <hi>Jone.</hi> 2. Free-will. 3. Falling from grace. 4. Conditionall Election, that men may be ſaved if they will themſelves. 5. They hold an univerſall Church, and generall miniſtery, with power univerſall. 6. That Antichriſt is not yet come, and ſhall be a particular man, and ſhall continue but three years, &amp;c. 7. They hold with Pope <hi>Jone,</hi> and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſure all the reformed and ſeparated Churches for meer Schiſmaticks. 8. They hold with Pope <hi>Jone</hi> dipping in Baptiſme. I do not ſay that <hi>J. S.</hi> or all of that way hold all theſe particulars; but this I am ſure, that all theſe are held by perſons in that way; in practice they alſo ſhake hands; for as the man of ſin hath made a Church, ſo they alſo have made a Church; onely the man of ſin and Pope <hi>Jone</hi> have ſucceeded better in their work, for they have made a Church of a large ſtructure; whereas theirs is yet but a little Terret of the like nature. 2. As Pope <hi>Joane</hi> hath ſent out her meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to preach and baptize; (namely, the Friers and others) the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:123379:32"/> Moors and Indians: ſo in like manner theſe ſend out their meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to preach and baptize alſo. 3. As Pope <hi>Jone</hi> and the man of ſin give authority to their inſtruments and miniſters to act things without the cognizance of the Scriptures, ſo in like kinde do they; namely, authorizing an unbaptized perſon to baptize others. In this and one thing more they exceed in irrationalneſſe Pope <hi>Ione;</hi> to wit, of giving <hi>miſſion to unbaptized</hi> perſons to baptize. 2. In <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing</hi> them that were before <hi>baptized.</hi> I will forbear to adde other particulars. Now let them ſhew if they can any ſuch doctrines held, or courſes taken by the ſeparated, or rightly reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in way of affinity with Pope <hi>Jone,</hi> and the man of ſin. I ſay no more, but leave the Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>In the end of this Sexion he uttereth divers high Notions, ſo undigeſted, unſound, and contradictorie, as a man that ſhould weigh them, could not but wonder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, he ſaith, that we are to know that the truth depends not upon Churches, nor any mortall creature, but onely upon the immortall God, who by his Word and Spirit reveals the ſame, when, and to whom he pleaſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the firſt of his wonderfull Notions, which we are to know, that the truth of Ordinances, and right ſerving God (of which is our queſtion) depends not upon Churches.</p>
               <p>Where then is <hi>J. S. his orderly way he propoſed according to God, by the Church and her aſſignement of one or two of her members, to begin Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, being loſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, This that he would have us to know, is directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which God teacheth us to know in his Word, 1 Tim. 3. 15. <hi>The Church of the living God, God himſelf ſaith, is the pillar and ground of truth:</hi> that is, of Religion and divine Ordinances, as we ſaid before.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If <hi>I. S.</hi> ſay, he do not mean truth of Ordinances, truly he is then beſide the matter in hand, deceiving and being deceived.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, If he mean as in the former is ſpecied, with whom then doth he contend? Do not all confeſſe the truth, as Doctrinall, to have God for the Authour of it, and to depend on him? What high words doth he here uſe to amaze the Reader? as, <hi>The truth depends not upon any mortall man.</hi> Who ever held ſo? <hi>But upon the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall God,</hi> Who ever held otherwiſe? <hi>But this immortall God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales the ſame by his Word and Spirit.</hi> What, doth God reveal new Ordinances of Religion by his Word and Spirit? Sure this is ſome
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:123379:32"/> dark non-ſenſe: He queſtionleſſe meaneth ſome other thing: What Revelation he herein intendeth, is not hard to gueſſe; however he is beſide the matter, and clean out in this firſt Notion.</p>
               <p>Second Notion: <hi>And for ſucceſſion of truth,</hi> (truth of Ordinances you muſt underſtand) <hi>It comes now by the promiſe of God, and faith of his people, whom he, as aforeſaid, hath taken out of the world to the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Setting aſide ſucceſſion, and in ſtead thereof putting in continuation; What can be more right then this, though not in <hi>J. S.</hi> his ſenſe? The truth of Ordinances continues by vertue of Gods promiſe made to his people, they continuing to beleeve in him, and not forgetting his name, though many times greatly fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt him, as of old; yet the truth of Ordinances continue; namely, the Church and Baptiſme now, as the Church and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion did of old; and this by the promiſe of God. <hi>J. S.</hi> hath no ſuch ſenſe as this, but ſome inward familiſticall ſenſe of inward faith, and Gods promiſe to ſuch ſecret beleevers; which he is never able to make out any ſuch thing, that the truth of Ordinances de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon them in regard of continuation, by vertee of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God to them in ſuch a ſecret way.</p>
               <p>Third Notion: <hi>To whom the Ordinances of Chriſt ſtand only by ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of faith</hi> (What faith, outward or inward?) <hi>and not of perſons</hi> (What faith ſevered from perſons?)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I would fain know what any rationall man can make of this, either in it ſelf, or as it hath relation to what is before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
               <p>Fourth Notion: <hi>For the ſame power the Apoſtles had in former time, for direction in godlineſſe, the Scriptures have in the hand of Chriſt, as the head of the Church, which make up but one body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> ſuch power for direction in godlineſſe, the Scriptures had of old, when the Apoſtles lived. Some other things <hi>J. S.</hi> aimeth at, but the truth prevaileth, and the words he here uſeth will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing avail: namely <hi>of the Scriptures in the hand of Chriſt joyned with the Church.</hi> Its worth obſerving how the Church is here couched, juſt after the manner of the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> that pretend their Church is inſpired with the Holy Ghoſt, and cannot erre: for Chriſt the head is in Heaven, and hath left his Word for direction in godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for his Church to take heed unto. Now the holy Apoſtles had authority to act Ordinances according to Chriſts command;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:123379:33"/> they were to preach, pray, break bread, and baptize; the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were not ſent, neither act they any thing as before. So as in <hi>J. S.</hi> his ſenſe, it is utterly untrue, that the Scriptures in the hand of Chriſt, joyned with the body, have the ſame power to act Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as the Apoſtles had.</p>
               <p>Notion fift and laſt, <hi>So as what the Apoſtles and Church together might do,</hi> (in acting Ordinances you muſt underſtand) <hi>the ſame may the head and body, together with the Scriptures, do now.</hi> Reader, obſerve how <hi>J. S.</hi> coucheth ſubtilly his unbaptized Church betwixt Chriſt and the Scriptures; ſo as Chriſt being in heaven, and the Scriptures only directive; the whole matter for action will fall into the hands of the Church. A contrivance, as fine as the Papiſt found out when they were ſore put to it by <hi>John Hus</hi> and the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> and not able to defend themſelves and their courſes againſt the truth, they invented and abetted this, <hi>That holy Church could not erre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, obſerve how <hi>I. S.</hi> quitteth two of theſe three; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the head and body: and concludeth laying all the ſtreſſe upon the Scriptures, and ſo in effect ſaith nothing at all, the Scriptures being only directive: for ſaith he, <hi>the Scriptures have the ſame,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ſhould have ſaid, the head and body, with the Scriptures, have it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, obſerve what a prepoſterous conjunction <hi>I. S.</hi> maketh of three, in the matter of fact; one of which, to wit Chriſt the head is in Heaven; who, though he hath fulneſſe of power, acts not here below, but in a providenciall, and miniſteriall way, and the like. The Church, the ſecond, Chriſts wife, is in all things to be obedient to Chriſt her husband, his will and pleaſure contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scripture: the Scriptures they act not, but only direct; where is <hi>I. S.</hi> now? juſt where he was at the firſt, and no further.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, this is utterly untrue, which he concludeth, <hi>that what the Church and the Apoſtles, the Miniſters of the Churches, might do; that the Scriptures</hi> (he quitteth the head and body as before) <hi>may do.</hi> Now, what might not the Church and the Apoſtles do, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and adminiſtration, orderly, according to God; what can the Scriptures act, truly nothing at all, their authority is only directive. I ſuppoſe any one may ſee how far out <hi>I. S.</hi> is in theſe conceits. In the cloſe he is up again with revelation, which happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if he did ſtudy and cleave unto, would ſtand him in more ſtead then the Scriptures that are ſo helpleſſe to him in his cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:123379:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Containing a defence of the opinion of them that hold no right or orderly Miniſteriall Church, without, or before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I. S. Having ended his former matter, againſt the Churches continuance, and likewiſe the continuance of Baptiſme under the popiſh defection, proceeds, ſaying,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo we come to ſuch as will have no Church before Baptiſme, and ſo make Baptiſme the form of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who theſe <hi>(ſuch)</hi> are that he intendeth, I cannot tell; they are either ſome of his own way, or ſome other: ſome of his own way do indeed ſo hold, that Baptiſme conſtitutes, or is the form of the Church. Did I think he intended them, I ſhould leave them to try it out, and ſhould not intermeddle with the ſtrife. I ſhall only, as the matter relates to them, ſhew my thoughts brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: namely, that they will be too hard for <hi>J. S.</hi> in the tenent, he himſelf being of their belief, but that he is not true to his owne principle: otherwiſe how ſhould he, without Schiſme, and being a Schiſmatick, leave the reformed and ſeparated Churches, and ſet up another of his own, as he hath done; only he accounteth them no Churches of Chriſt, and what is the reaſon he doth ſo? no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his Baptiſme is wanting, ſo as that muſt be the form that gives being; for otherwiſe, <hi>They are companies of Saints profeſſing faith in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and living accordingly; that is, in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life.</hi> This he deſcribeth to be the matter, and the form he declareth to be <hi>their being united and knit together in one fellowſhip or orderly body; and that is the Covenant of grace by which God becomes</hi> (not viſibly, as he unawars ſaith) <hi>but in an outward way of relation, a God unto them, and they become viſibly his people.</hi> Now what is there to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>J. S.</hi> from being a Schiſmatick by his own ground: for ſurely nothing hinders thoſe Churches which he forſaketh and diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, as no Churches of Chriſt, by all or any thing, that in his deſcription of the matter or form of the Church, by him ſet down
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:123379:34"/> can be found: and let him take in his five Reaſons to help him if he pleaſe. So as it muſt be the want of his new Baptiſme or nothing, and then I leave it to him to judge, whether that be not the form of the Church neceſſarily, according to his ground that gives the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if by <hi>(ſuch)</hi> he meanes thoſe he was an opponent of in the former matter of the Churches continuation, and likewiſe Baptiſme under Popiſh defection: I ſhall adde a little in the way of defence.</p>
               <p>Firſt, granting that ſuch hold indeed no Church (to wit, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſtituted, as a right or lawfull Miniſteriall Church) without or before the matter of this Church is baptized.</p>
               <p>Secondly, denying that in ſo holding, they make Baptiſme the form of the Church, as he inferreth, <hi>(and ſo make Baptiſme the form,)</hi> there is more goeth to the proof of a matter then ſo.</p>
               <p>His five Reaſons might well have been ſpared, by which he would prove Baptiſme, not to be the form of the Church, till he had made that to appear to be of neceſſity the right conſequence, which ſure he is never able to do: for there was no right Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Church of old without Circumciſion, yet Circumciſion was not the form of that Church: an uncircumciſed perſon was not to be admitted a member, much leſſe an officer Circumciſion was then an externall qualification of the matter; as in like manner is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme now.</p>
               <p>In this matter we ſhall have recourſe to the firſt beginning of the Church of the new Teſtament, and of Baptiſme. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt the forerunner of Chriſt, ſent of God, to prepare the way of his Son, according to Commiſſion, baptized much people, as did alſo afterward the Diſciples of Chriſt our Lord: to him repaired our Lord to be baptized, that righteouſneſſe might be fulfilled. It may be obſerved by the way, that this was in the Church of the <hi>Jewes.</hi> Of theſe thus baptized was the Church of the new Teſtament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, whether the initiation of it be referred to the time before the paſſion of our Lord, as to himſelf and the twelve, with whom he brake bread, or whether it be referred to the time after his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, when he <hi>gathered the</hi> 120. <hi>together and bleſſed them,</hi> (as is moſt <note place="margin">Acts 1.</note> proper) let him take his choice, and refer to which he will, it was begun of the aforeſaid baptized matter, which is certainly to the life of the matter in hand, in diſcovering that the matter of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:123379:34"/> Church was fitted by Baptiſme before it was laid together. As was the Church at the firſt riſe of it, ſo was the proceed: thoſe 120. baptized, thoſe that joyned with them (being not before baptized) as it is written, <hi>they were baptized and added to the Church.</hi> This firſt Church ſcattered by perſecution, became the inſtrument of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and the firſt matter of many Churches; which Churches by their inſtruments, baptized ſuch as <hi>received the faith, and joyned into the Lord,</hi> and thus was the Church and Kingdome of Chriſt ſpread throughout the World, as the holy hiſtory doth ſhew. And let <hi>J. S.</hi> or any of his way, ſhew that there was ever any unbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Church or Congregation of the new Teſtament, or that ever any unbaptized perſon was received into fellowſhip, or that ever any unbaptized perſon, after Baptiſme was a foot in the World baptiſed, or was authorized for to do it. And laſtly, let him tell me, whether the order of the new Teſtament, (as in another caſe he asked,) be not as ſtrict in this caſe of Baptiſme, as it was in Circumciſion of old, when no uncircumciſed might have part in the Church, or fellowſhip in the <hi>Ordinances,</hi> much leſſe act Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances <note place="margin">Eſek. 44.</note> in way of diſpenſing of them to others. And let him tell me, whether a precept or example be not as neceſſary in all thoſe caſes, as in that of baptizing Infants. And laſtly, whether his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of raiſing and beginning the Church of unbaptized perſons, do agree with the primitive practice of our Lord and his Apoſtles, that began the Church of baptized matter, as before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. S.</hi> propoundeth a ſecond Reaſon of his opponents thus, <hi>The Scripture ſpeaketh of no Church before Baptiſme.</hi> To which he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as he did to that of the Gates of Hell not prevailing againſt the Church: <hi>He muſt diſtinguiſh, he ſaith.</hi> A meer ſhift to blind his Reader, and avoid the truth; there needs no diſtinction at all in the caſe. He would not take it well, if any ſhould diſtinguiſh in caſe of Infants Baptiſme. But what is his diſtinction, <hi>it is betwixt the truth of the doctrine of Baptiſme, and the adminiſtration of it</hi> (juſt as he did in the fore-named caſe) as much as if he had ſaid, <hi>He muſt diſtinguiſh</hi> betwixt the Scripture that teacheth Baptiſme, and Baptiſme or waſhing according to the Scripture. In this firſt ſenſe, Baptiſme or the doctrine of Baptiſme (as much as if he had ſaid, the holy word of God) <hi>is before the Church:</hi> What this is to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is beyond my judgement; nor yet that which followeth: <hi>no Church according to the order of Chriſts Teſtament without it or before it.</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:123379:35"/> No Church without or before the Scripture; how this is to the matter in hand, and what clearing (or rather darkning) there is in this diſtinction, I leave the Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>But now for the ſecond part of the diſtinction: Namely, <hi>the outward adminiſtration of Baptiſme that ever followeth the Saints joyning in fellowſhip, by mutuall faith and agreement in the Doctrine, wherein conſiſts the ſtating of the Church in her conjoyning in Covenant, which ever goes before in the adminiſtration of Baptiſme, and gives power and authority for the ſame;</hi> ſo, ſaith he, <hi>in the firſt ſenſe the Church is not before Baptiſme, but in the laſt it is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſumme and ſcope of this whole matter amplified and enlarged, is utterly falſe, being referred to the purpoſe for which <hi>J. S.</hi> doth bring it, namely to prove an unbaptized Church, or the Scriptures ſpeaking of ſuch. Alas, this is farre from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the matter; no not in a ſeeming way. In this caſe it may be truly ſaid, <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo:</hi> The matter of the Church was fitted outwardly by Baptiſme, as is before declared: And the Scriptures give no preſident of ſuch Church, officer, or member, at any time ſuch a proceed being cleane beſides the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>J. S.</hi> deceiveth (if not himſelfe) yet others in what he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth down; in referring that to the initiation of a Church, which is onely true of the proceed. The Church ſtated and on foot in the world, according to God, of baptized perſons, baptizeth others in way of proceed, in a orderly way of adminiſtration; ſo it was at the beginning, and to begin otherwiſe is not according to the pattern. So as not taking notice of the difference, between right beginning and orderly proceed, he is clean out, and beſide the truth, and his diſtinction will appeare to be vain and to no purpoſe unleſſe to deceive; for as he ſetteth down, that Baptiſme ever followeth in regard of the adminiſtration of it, the Saints joyning in fellowſhip, &amp;c. this is onely true of the proceed of the Church as before; but this joyning is to be of baptized matter, as it was at the beginning, which neceſſarily calleth either for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from heaven, as in the inſtance of <hi>John,</hi> or the continuance of baptized perſons in the world from <hi>John</hi> downward, as is the caſe now, though <hi>J. S.</hi> will not acknowledge the ſame. The ſum of the diſtinction he maketh to be this in the firſt ſence, the Church is not before the Scriptures. In the laſt ſenſe, it is before Baptiſme; utterly untrue, as before.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:123379:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. S.</hi> telleth us, <hi>his diſtinction being obſerved, we are not to deny a Church to be a Church, though the Scriptures doe not ſo call it.</hi> So the Scriptures of which he ſpake ſo great things in caſe of raiſing Baptiſme loſt, are now become deficient, and we may be wiſer then they teach us; and call a people a Church, though they doe not ſo call them or teach us ſo to doe and we are not ſo ingaged: to ſpeak <hi>as the Word of God.</hi> His reaſon of this ſtrange divinity <hi>is the Church of the Old Teſtament, and many of the new were Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were ſo called.</hi> But I ſay they were not rightly gathered Churches before they were baptized, neither doth the Scriptures give that appellation to any in a relative way to Chriſt, and we may not be <hi>wiſe above what is written. Cornelius</hi> and his friends coming together, were no right orderly gathered Church before Baptiſme, neither doth the Scripture ſo call them. After all ſaid that may be, he demandeth, <hi>why it may not be ſo, that a Church may be a Church before Baptiſme be adminiſtred:</hi> why may not children be baptized, I would aske him? let him tell me that, I will tell him why.</p>
               <p>Againe he ſaith, <hi>a Church is ſo a Church before Baptiſme, as that the end of her union is for communion. J. S.</hi> at the laſt doth in effect in a modeſt way give up the cauſe; <hi>(A Church ſo a Church)</hi> That is, in another way then at the beginning it was, when it was firſt inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Againe in another way, then according to a right Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and orderly way of ſerving God. Again, is a <hi>Church ſo</hi> as a betrothed Virgin is a wife before the day of her Eſpouſlas, and playeth the Harlot in the mean time, and ſo defileth the marriage bed: So is an unbaptized Church a Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>After this he is up with the ſubſtance of his five Reaſons before alledged, to prove that <hi>Baptiſme was not the forme of the Church, but the Covenant.</hi> And what then? (for I will not meddle with his Reaſons, be they right or wrong.) <hi>A Church may be in Covenant and fellowſhip before Baptiſme be adminiſtred</hi> (ſo as <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his friends were:) But I ſay ſuch a Church can never adminiſter Baptiſme according to God, unleſſe they had a man ſent to them, as <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſent, or as <hi>Peter</hi> was to <hi>Cornelius and his friends.</hi> He is pleaſed to call ſuch a Church, whom the Scripture calleth not ſo. But what he here ſetteth down he doth as formerly, but ſay it and not prove it, ſo as we need not much ſtand upon it. <hi>A People are a Church by covenant, he ſaith, to which Ordinances are annexed:</hi> But
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:123379:36"/> the matter of this Church is to be firſt outwardly ſitted by Baptiſm. An orderly way is neceſſary, and that is by perſons ſent of God, as was <hi>John;</hi> here he deceiveth again, affirming that of <hi>(his ſo a Church)</hi> which is onely true of a Church ſtated, and on foot, according to God in the world, as was the Church of the new Teſtament bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and ſo the matter outwardly ſitted by <hi>John</hi> before the building was erected.</p>
               <p>He quoteth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 8. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 41. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 5. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth thus: <hi>So here was a Church before Ordinances, or before ever Baptiſme was adminiſtred, either by</hi> John the Baptiſt, <hi>or the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, in regard of thoſe two places of the old Teſtament, alledged in this matter in queſtion: It is at leaſt as far off as the proving the baptizing of Infants from Circumciſion, or their being baptized <hi>of old to</hi> Moſes <hi>in the cloud and ſea,</hi> which he <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.</note> accounteth nothing to the purpoſe, as indeed this is little to the purpoſe. They uſe to ask in the inſtance before, when produced: whether that Baptiſme of the cloud, &amp;c. was the Baptiſme of the new Teſtament. I in like manner ask him whether thoſe were the miniſteriall Churches of the new Teſtament. Alas, this matter is too far fetcht. I could tell him of a Church, and a great one too, without faith, or the profeſſion of it: namely, that gathered by <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius and his fellow Crafts-men, Act.</hi> 19. 25. 46. he happily will count it to no purpoſe; truly, ſo is his matter here.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe inſtances in the new Teſtament, ſure he was much over-ſeen in them, and very inconſiderate: Thoſe <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 41. <hi>had broken bread, and prayed, and were baptized, before</hi> they were a Church. As for the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> no queſtion but that was alſo bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in like manner; and he might from that place as well prove a Church to be before faith, as before Baptiſme, by any thing I can perceive. Certainly he had little aim, in bringing ſuch places of Scripture to prove a people to be a Church of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before Baptiſme was adminiſtred to them; at leaſt that it ſhould be ſo before <hi>Johns Baptiſme,</hi> that according to the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of God, adminiſtred Baptiſme to fit the matter of the Church, before ever it was laid into form.</p>
               <p>A further Objection he ſetteth down thus: <hi>Some ſay from</hi> Act. 2. 41. <hi>they were added to the Church after they were baptized.</hi> What is his Anſwer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If it were ſo; they ſhould neither put on Chriſt, nor yet be baptized into</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:123379:36"/> 
                  <hi>one body, nor to the true profeſſion of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, &amp;c. directly againſt theſe Scriptures,</hi> Gal. 3. 27. 1 Cor. 12. 13. Matth. 28. 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I am very ſorry to ſee ſuch weakneſſe in perſons preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to, and promiſing much ſtrength of knowledge. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, all thoſe that <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> baptized, could neither put on Chriſt, nor be baptized into one body, nor into the true profeſſion of the Father, &amp;c. by his account and reckoning; and ſo his practice of baptizing was contrary to thoſe Scriptures by his reckoning. Was not <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> to blame?</p>
               <p>Secondly, how appeareth it, that if perſons ſent <hi>of God, as was John</hi> of old, (as is neceſſary to raiſe Baptiſme, if it were loſt out of the world, as they hold) baptizing according to their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that thoſe they baptize cannot put on Chriſt, nor be baptized into one body, nor into the true profeſſion of the Trinity, onely becauſe <hi>J. S.</hi> ſaith ſo, without any ſhew of ground. For,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, thoſe Scriptures cited, have no ſuch thing in them certainly to the judgement of any rationall man; neither can it be imagined that there is any let in regard of any of them, why a perſon ſent of God ſhould not baptize before the Church be formed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For that in</hi> Acts 2. 41. <hi>he ſaith, It is onely declarative of the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Church through Gods goodneſſe.</hi> To which I anſwer; That it declareth plainly, that they were of, and by that Church bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, that they were added unto, in as much as the Church recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth no unwaſhen ones. If it were queſtioned whether the Church receive them before ſhe baptize them, or baptize them before ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them; I would give my thoughts, that in ſtrictneſſe of conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, neither are firſt; for theſe are ſo interwoven, that they go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; are unſeparable: As thus, perſons beleeving (being unbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed) the Church openeth her arms to receive them, but before ſhe can fully imbrace them, they muſt be waſhed, and ſo made like the reſt of the body. There is a different caſe to be taken knowledge of:</p>
               <p>Firſt, of the ſeed of the Church (by generation I mean) they are of the Church firſt, and baptized for righteouſneſſe ſake, becauſe they are of the Church, and for the end before ſpecified.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the caſe of converted Infidels; their acceſſe to the Church and Ordinances is as before; as it was in like manner of old in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the infants were circumciſed, becauſe they were a part of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they might anſwer the whole. But the Converts of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:123379:37"/> the Nations they were circumciſed, that they might be of the Church, and have fellowſhip in the ſame. The caſe I conceive to be even ſo now, which I note in way of digreſſion, as a touch to be <note place="margin">Exod. 12. 48.</note> conſidered of, though happily <hi>J. S.</hi> will think it to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>There is another Argument, which he ſetteth down, and maketh anſwer unto; all the difference amounteth but to that of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of time, and hath nothing in it ſubſtantiall; I ſhall not make the difference greater, but ſhall leave <hi>J. S.</hi> to his conſtituting cauſes of his unbaptized Church, and ſhall forbear to trouble him, or my ſelf, or the Reader any further, but leave all to the judgement of the godly wiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:123379:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 11. l. 20. <hi>for</hi> Infants, <hi>r.</hi> Intents. p. 13. l. 16. <hi>for</hi> ſhrine, <hi>r.</hi> ſhrinke. p. 14. l. 36. <hi>for</hi> and priviledge, <hi>r.</hi> a priviledge. p. 45. l. 34. <hi>for</hi> conſtitation, <hi>r.</hi> conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
